<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Morbus polyrhizos et polymorphæus. A treatise of the scurvy. Examining opinions and errors, concerning the nature and cure of this disease. Establishing a method for prevention and cure, founded upon other principles; concordant with reason, verified by practice. By Everard Maynwaringe Doctor in Physick.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1764:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Morbus polyrhizos et polymorphæus. A treatise of the scurvy. Examining opinions and errors, concerning the nature and cure of this disease. Establishing a method for prevention and cure, founded upon other principles; concordant with reason, verified by practice. By Everard Maynwaringe Doctor in Physick.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 61, [5], 65-94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.D. for T. Basset under S. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Anticorbutick medecines" has separate title page dated 1664; register is continuous; pagination more or less continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scurvy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MORB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S POLYRHIZOS</hi> ET <hi>POLYMORPHAE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> A TREATISE OF THE SCURVY.</p>
                  <p>Examining Opinions and Errors, concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Cure of this Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>ESTABLISHING A Method for prevention and cure, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon other principles; concordant with Reaſon, verified by Practice.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Everard Maynwaringe</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num hoc Medicus recte agit, quod recte cognoſcit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> under S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1665.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:2"/>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Ex aedibus Lamb. <date>Sept. 9. 1664.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Tho. Cooke Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo Patri ac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino D. Gilb. Arch. Cant. a Sacris.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To The Right Honourable</hi> MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E BERTIE <hi>Earl of</hi> Lindſey, Lord Great Chamberlain of <hi>England,</hi> of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councel, Knight of the moſt Noble order of the Garter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ealth being of ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable a conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that without it, the beſt temporal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments are inſipid; and rather may be termed repreſentations and ſhadows then really fruitions, and therefore the <hi>Phioloſopher</hi> ſaid truly, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:3"/>
                  <p>The buſineſs of this little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual, is for preſervation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of that invaluable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, which ſeaſons, and gives a pleaſant reliſh to mundane hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and felicity.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, I have not uſed your name in a ſmall concernment and inconſiderable matter; 'tis a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick affair wherein all are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſſed.</p>
                  <p>This ſcene repreſents the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tean ſhapes and deluſive actings or motions of a ſubtile Impoſtor; or rather, diſcovers a combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Diſeaſes, liſted in hoſtility to break the Peace and diſorder the regular government of the Microcoſm, and conſequently to ruine it; and having undertaken to diſcover, oppoſe and extirpate
<pb facs="tcp:30768:3"/>theſe Confederates, and break their aſſociation; I have aſſumed this boldneſs to invite your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Prize: and ſeeing ſo great a Champion ſtand by to view the conteſt, puts me in mind of what is truly noble, exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and renowned: for looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, I ſee a pattern of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of fortitude and skil at arms, which you inherit from your Anceſtors of moſt worthy memory, who have defied the fiery breath and thundering voice of Canon; From whoſe ſides the Loyal Sword of Honour hath oft ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared naked, to vindicate the Truth of Royal intereſt, and a Kingdoms ſafety: and what not, worthy to be recorded?</p>
                  <p>To you therefore, My Lord, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer
<pb facs="tcp:30768:4"/>of Arts and Learning, are theſe endeavours peculiarly offered; waiting this opportunity to make my acknowledgments for Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours favour and kindneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and to let the World know the reſpects I bear to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Family, and that I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Honours Moſt devoted Servant.</hi> Everard Maynwaringe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:4"/>
                  <head>Viro Doctiſsimo, <hi>Amico ſuo ſingulari D. Dri.</hi> Everardo Maynwaringe <hi>Medico Peritiſſimo.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>S. Pergratae mihi fuerunt literae tuae, amice plurimum colende benevolentiae &amp; candoris in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municando pleniſſimae: verae &amp; conſtantis amicitiae (abhinc diu in <hi>America</hi> contractae, poſtea hîc fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter continuatae) ſymbolum &amp; munus gratiſſimum. Gratias habeo maximas pro communicatis; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebunt &amp; omnes pro tuis accuratè in ſcorbuto tractando laboribus (cum publici juris fuerint) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gni ſane aeſtimandis, ſerioque ab omnibus notandis.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:5"/>
                  <p>Quamobrem multum deſidero, moram omnem abjicias, atque the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurum illum miſeris ubicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buticis feliciter a perias; ut medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tua eximia antiſcorbutica (ſecundum leges ſpagyricae artis quam peritiſſime concinnata.) Communi bono nulli etiam la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teant; ut &amp; languentibus, varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hoc morbo cruciatis eorum auxilio quam primum ſuccurras.</p>
                  <p>Plura notatu digna (vere &amp; fine blanditiis dico) tuis ſcriptis repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio: grata manu ea quidem me accepiſſe fateor. Perge itaque tu, quod facis: faxitque Deus, omnia tua ſtudia, in aegrotantium exopta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam valetudinem &amp; nominis tui fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, feliciter cedant; de quibus nihil dubito.</p>
                  <p>Hiſce vale, &amp; memoriam mei
<pb facs="tcp:30768:5"/>quod hactenus benigne feciſti, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine: meque promptum &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantem in omnibus promitto. <hi>dab. Dublinii. Calend. Septemb.</hi> 1664.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Chriſtophorus Laurentius. <hi>Med. Doctor.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:6"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the complaints of the diſeaſed none more frequently mentioned than the Scurvy, and none leſs known, except by its title: moſt of them ſhewing a ſeveral character of the diſeaſe, and in ſeveral parts; ſome ſpots in this place, others in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and different colours: ſome looſneſs of teeth, putrid gums, ill ſavoured breath; pains in ſeveral parts, weakneſs of the legs and thighs, laſſitude and indiſpoſition to motion or action, and other ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms accompanying this Protean diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:30768:6"/>
                  <p>And although the ſigns be many which diſcover the Diſeaſe, yet to the moſt they are rather a diſguiſe (ſave only the name Scurvy) to cheat their Judgment, than a guide to lead them into the knowledge and diſcovery of it, from what cauſes, its chief ſeat of reſidence, and manner of generation.</p>
                  <p>The variety of ſpotted faces and dreſſes that this Diſeaſe puts on, and preſents it ſelf in; the variety of places and parts of the body, differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in conſtitution, fabrication, and office, that this takes up for its quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and aboad; diſplaying it ſelf in colours above board, and yet a jugler, deceiving and deluding, that comparing one ſign with another, they diſown their alliance as Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gene, and ſeem to claſh one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother as if they were not the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of the ſame Parents, the fruit and productions from the ſame ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix.</p>
                  <p>Hence variety of opinions and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb facs="tcp:30768:7"/>concerning the nature of this diſeaſe; and from falſe principles, erroneous practices in the cure have enſued, and is proſecuted by many ineffectually and fruſtraneouſly; which cauſeth many Scorbutick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to think and ſay their diſeaſe is incurable: for having undergone ſo many courſes in Phyſick ſpring and fall, and tryed variety of Medicines; yet they are the ſame, or benefited but a little, or for a ſhort time, the ſymptoms only abated, and nature alleviated for a while; but ſoon after they return to their former condition, or worſe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe conſiderations moved me to ventilate this ſubject, as well for my own ſatisfaction and more certainty in the cure thereof; as alſo to inform others; and by a ſtrict diſquiſition and ſerious examination, tracing ſtep by ſtep; made diſcoveries of errors which paſſed for warrantable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable truths, being ſupported by the authorities of Learned and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb facs="tcp:30768:7"/>Authors: and being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſatisfied Theoretically and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically, I cannot but recede from ſome opinions, which before tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly I maintained, being nouriſhed and bred up in thoſe doctrines.</p>
                  <p>I have not therefore beſtowed theſe pains for an affected ſingularity, to gain popular applauſe, or be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a noveliſt and innovator; but that the dictates of reaſon, confirmed by obſervation and practice, have cauſed me to diſſent from the common opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for being fruſtrate of my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in effecting cures by the uſual method, eſtabliſhed upon unſound prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; was urged to make inquiries into the cauſes from whence ſuch fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and failings did ariſe, and being ſufficiently perſwaded and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied herein; have therefore deſerted the uſual method and Medicines, for that which is more certain and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; as the Medicines ſubjoyned will teſtifie theſe truths to thoſe that ſhall prove them: and although hete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dox in
<pb facs="tcp:30768:8"/>the proſecution of this work, I have inſerted nothing for oſtentation, or aemulation towards others, or biaſſed with affectation of ſubtilities; but contending for the truth and benefit of the diſeaſed, is the ſcope and aim of theſe endeavours.</p>
                  <p>If any diſguſted at what is delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thinking their own opinions hereby injured; I ſhall ſtand by theſe aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and reply to the opponent.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>E. M.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi> Next the <hi>Blew Boar</hi> on <hi>Ludgate-Hill.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <group>
               <text xml:lang="eng">
                  <front>
                     <div type="title_page">
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:8"/>
                        <p>ADVERTISEMENT, <hi>Tutela Sanitatis</hi> SIVE <hi>VITA PROTRACTA.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Protection of long life and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of its brevity, from diaetetick cauſes and cuſtoms.</p>
                        <p>Wholſom Precautions, <hi>Theorems</hi> and daily Practical Rules for the Preſervation of Health and Prolongation of life.</p>
                        <p>WITH A TREATISE of Fontinels or Iſſues.</p>
                        <p>By <hi>Everard Maynwaringe</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
                        <p>Sold by <hi>S. Thompſon</hi> at the Biſhops head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> under St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> Bookſellers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="errata">
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:9"/>
                        <head>ERRATA.</head>
                        <p>Page 13. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>read</hi> ſeparated, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 19. barely, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 25. air, ☞ <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 12. parts, ☞ <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>read</hi> ſtomack and ſpleen, <hi>p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 25. obedience.</p>
                     </div>
                  </front>
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30768:9"/>
                           <head>NAMES Given to the SCURVEY.</head>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iſeaſes, for the moſt part, have ſignificant Names, whoſe Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology diſcovers either the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Diſeaſe: as, <hi>Hydrops</hi> the Dropſie, from <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>aqua,</hi> water; or points at the part principally, or primarily affected: as <hi>Pluritis</hi> the Plurifie, from that Membrane compaſſing the breſt, called <hi>Pleura.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Or intimates the manner of invaſion; as <hi>Epilepſia</hi> the Epilepſie, from <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendo,</hi> to ſeiz, or take ſuddenly.</p>
                           <p>Or denotes the procuring cauſe; as <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> the Venerial Pox.</p>
                           <p>Or declares the manner of afflicting, as <hi>Convulſion,</hi> from <hi>Convello</hi> to pluck.</p>
                           <pb n="2" facs="tcp:30768:10"/>
                           <p>With many other, whoſe Names do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and carry various ſignifications perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and declarative, which for brevity ſake I omit. That which I have particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to handle, is the <hi>Scorbute,</hi> or <hi>Scurvy</hi> in the Engliſh tongue; but in other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, denoting ſome part ſymptomatically affected: In the Daniſh 'tis called <hi>Schorbect,</hi> ſignifying a vitious depravedneſs in the mouth, becauſe in many it was diſcovered by looſneſs of Teeth, and putrefaction of Gums, to which the Greek name agrees, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</p>
                           <p>In the Low-Countries 'tis called <hi>Schor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunct,</hi> ſignifying torſions or gripings in the belly, which attend this diſeaſe in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                           <p>It is alſo called <hi>Scelotyrbe,</hi> from the ſpots and pains in the thighs: It hath been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſome <hi>Gingipedium,</hi> from the Gums and feet, that frequently are affected in this diſeaſe.</p>
                           <p>The Latin word <hi>Scorbutùs,</hi> now moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently uſed among Phyſitians, being a name not of long ſtanding, unknown to the Ancients, and therefore called by ſome a new diſeaſe, but falſly; and it is not againſt Reaſon to think this diſeaſe to be of as great antiquity, as moſt infirmities incident to the body, (as may appear hereafter) though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30768:10"/>known by divers appellations, ſuting with ſome of the ſymptoms, or products that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this Diſeaſe, yet inſufficiently and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly diſcovered in their Cauſes.</p>
                           <p>Concerning the ſeveral Names, whether proper or improper, I ſhall not inſiſt, the nature of the Diſeaſe being the thing aimed at to be detected and proſecuted, and not to ſpend time upon words.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>How to diſcern the Scurvey in its va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſigns, ſymptoms or products, and complications with other infirmities.</head>
                           <p>IN the diſquiſition and ſearch to know and find out the nature of this Diſeaſe, I muſt ſurvey the concomitant effects and products of it, which diſcover its being, gradual ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, fortitude or progreſs, and parts affected or infected, though not the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Spring and Riſe thereof.</p>
                           <p>Many and various are the Symptoms which accompany this Diſeaſe, though all do not appear in every Perſon, but ſome more, ſome fewer, according to the greatneſs, durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and progreſs of it.</p>
                           <p>The Morbific diſpoſition and debility of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30768:11"/>parts to conſent, degenerate, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved. <hi>Propter inaequale robur partium,</hi> by reaſon of the Natural integrity, and defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, Fortitude and imbecility of Parts in divers Perſons; ſome have one Part ſtrong, and vigorous in its Office, not eaſily depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and vitiated: another hath the ſame Part weak, ſoon conſenting with any Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, eaſily perverted from the integrity of its Office, and contributing its vice: And ſince the parts be divers, their Uſe and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces various; their enormities, vitioſities and defections alſo muſt be various, and their effects diſſimilar, heterogene and unlike, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the conſent and diſſent of Parts, in their integrities and defections.</p>
                           <p>Which being rightly underſtood, it is no wonder that the <hi>Scurvy</hi> appears in divers colours and ſhapes, acting a part here and there in the body, in various difformities; We ſhall not need then to fly to the admix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Humours, and diverſity of Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to derive the variety of Symptoms charging the innocent, and freeing the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Parts.</p>
                           <p>Now as the ſeveral Parts in the Body have their ſeveral Offices diſtinct from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet all harmoniouſly (in the rectitude of Nature) cooperating ſubſerviently and ſubordinately for the preſervation and well-fare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30768:11"/>of the whole; ſo is there diſtinct Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters for their duties and deficiencies, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering which part acts in integrity, and which is irregular, degenerates and falls off.</p>
                           <p>From hence the <hi>Scorbute,</hi> as it is variega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſcordant in the Symptoms and Products, which cheats the judgment of many, and puzles them to appropriate a fit Medicine; yet may the able Phyſitian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by collect and find out the conſpiring and contributing Parts to the difformity of this Diſeaſe, which rightly known, the difficulty of the Cure is much abated.</p>
                           <p>Some complain of laxity, and breaking out often into fluxes; others complain of coſtiveneſs, but a ſtool in 2, 3 or 4 daies; ſome complain of burning and fluſhing heats; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their limbs are rigid and ſtiff with cold, the bloud ſetled, black and livid.</p>
                           <p>Some are heavy, drowſy and ſleepy; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tired and worn out with watching, and indiſpoſed to the Nights refreſhment; ſome have a ſlow, weak, languid pulſe; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a quick, fierce, leaping Pulſe.</p>
                           <p>Some have thin, pale, watery Urine; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thick, muddy, and high coloured U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
                           <p>Some have black, looſe Teeth, and putrid Gums; the thighs and legs free from pains
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30768:12"/>or ſpots; others the contrary, have ſpots and pains, but the Teeth and Gums ſound.</p>
                           <p>Some are moleſted with erratick wandring pains from part to part; others more fixed and conſtant in particular Parts.</p>
                           <p>Some their Bodies pine away, waſt and are conſumptive; others grow corpulent, ſwell'd and puffed up.</p>
                           <p>Some complain of ſhortneſs of Breath, ſtraitneſs and compreſſion of the Breaſt, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult or hard breathing, &amp; palpitation of the heart; others their vital parts are more free, but complain of the Head, Hypochonders, and loins, loſs of appetite, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>Some are moleſted with thirſt, heat of the Stomack, and drineſs of Mouth; others are troubled with ſalivation, ſuperfluous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and ſpitting.</p>
                           <p>The variety of oppoſite and different Symptoms, which accompany the <hi>Scorbute,</hi> do ſtartle many in their judgment, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin certainly when they meet with the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> when not; and becauſe the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms are not peculiar but common, and the effects of other Diſeaſes as well as the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> it is no wonder if their Cure be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, difficult and ſeldome performed, ſince they are equivocal effects, obſcured in their cauſes by a dubious complication, and alternative cauſation.</p>
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:30768:12"/>
                           <p>To reſolve the ambiguous, and ſuch as ſtagger in their judgments; Take theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Corollaries.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="1">1. Many are the Symptoms which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and follow this Diſeaſe, which appear and vaniſh, are greater and leſſer, as the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe encreaſeth or diminiſheth in its eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial primitive Cauſes.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Many are the Products and off-ſpring of this Diſeaſe, which exiſt afterwards of their own ability and enormity, having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the parts wherein they reſide, and drawn them to conſent with their vitioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. Many Diſeaſes are complicated with the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> which had not their producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and generation from it, nor is their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of it, though probably made worſe and exaſperated by it.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. That none of the Smpytoms or Signs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, ſingly do declare the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> to be preſent in the Body, but may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge other cauſes for their Parents; and therefore to judge and determine that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Scorbutick, barely from the appearance of any Sign or Symptom that frequently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies the Scorbute, his judgment is fallible and uncertain and erroneous in the dependance: for, any Symptom or Sign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing in any part of the Body, uſually atri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30768:13"/>to the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> may be the peculiar defect of that part, or effect of ſome occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal cauſe, without a praevious Scorbutick diſpoſition.</p>
                           <p n="5">5. That the ſubſequent digeſtions have their proper errors and degenerations, from a ſpontaneous defection and laſſitude in their vital principles, without diſturbance from an injurious object, tranſmitted by errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preceding digeſtions, or improper <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſua natura;</hi> whoſe effects are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar and equivalent to ſome Products and Symptoms of the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> therefore to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh and know aright to whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, and whence they had their riſe, is by examining each faculty in their proper Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of rectitude and declenſions.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. That the Diagnoſtic Signs of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe uſually ſo accounted and moſt frequent, as defects in the mouth, pains, ſpots, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, laſſitude, &amp;c. ſome or more; antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cauſes concurring, ſome or more; as a cloſe Chamber air, and confinement within doors; or a Region where the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical, groſs food, ſedentary, inactive, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired Life, ſtudious, melancholly diſpoſition, or ſplenetic, indulging ſleep and eaſe: In the concurrence of theſe cauſes collated with the Signs mentioned, a certain determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and judgment of the Diſeaſe will reſult;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30768:13"/>and from thence a certain proceſs in the Cure may enſue:</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Examination of opinions concerning the nature of the Scurvy.</head>
                           <p>BEfore I explicate the nature, quiddity, or eſſence of this Prothean Diſeaſe, I ſhall firſt recite the judgments and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the moſt learned and eminent Phyſitians that have writ upon this Subject, to whom the moſt of our age do adhere, and imitate their practice in the Cure. <hi>Senner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> gives this definition or deſcription of it.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Scorbutus eſt prava &amp; occulta qualitas, ſeu diſpoſitio, toti corpori, praecipue vero viſceribus nutritioni dicatis impreſſa, ab humore melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholico craſſo, ſeroſo ſeu ichoroſo, peculiari modo corrupto orta; cum ſpontaneae laſſitudinis &amp; gravitatis, in cruribus praecipue, ſenſu; pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris anguſtia &amp; reſpirationis difficultate, gingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varum corruptione, &amp; oris graveolentia ac ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis purpureis in cruribus inprimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>, aliiſque morbis, ac ſymptomatibus plurimis ab eadem cauſa pendentibus, conjuncta.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>He ſaith, It is an evil occult quality, or diſpoſition, impreſſed upon the whole body,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30768:14"/>chiefly the Parts deſtinated for nutrition, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from a groſs melancholly or ſerous i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorous humour after a peculiar manner corrupted with laſſitude and heavineſs.</p>
                           <p>This Definition looks imperfect and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>An evil occult Quality.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here's a <hi>ne plus ultra</hi> to our enquiry, if we would ſit down here, and be contented only to know, that we know not what it is; an occult quality.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A Quality.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here he makes the Diſeaſe to be <hi>accidens,</hi> when as it is <hi>ens ſubſtantiale habens propriam radicem in vitali principio.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ariſing from a groſs melancholy, or ſerous i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorous humour after a peculiar manner corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>To find out this groſs melancholy, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ichorous humour peculiarly ſo corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is the ſame task as to find out the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult quality; this is <hi>ignotum per ignotum,</hi> to deſcribe one unknown thing by another. The <hi>Scurvy</hi> does not ariſe from a groſſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly; that's a groſſe error, or a ſerous ichorous humour: but if the Scorbutic de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved humour may go under thoſe deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, they are the effects of the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> and not the cauſe; you muſt dig deeper to find the radix of the Diſeaſe.</p>
                           <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30768:14"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Chiefly the parts deſtinated for Nutrition.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here he ſaies the <hi>Scurvey</hi> is an evil diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion impreſſed upon the Parts for Nutrition; but I muſt ſay it is chiefly ariſing from the Parts deſtinated and appointed for Nutriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which difference is as great, as between the <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> and the <hi>terminus ad quem.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Impreſſed upon the wholo body.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here is the Diſeaſe in <hi>facto eſſe,</hi> and its progreſſe, but from whence it ſprung as yet is not diſcovered, you muſt return back and trace it farther, if you will ſee it <hi>in fieri,</hi> in its generation; <hi>in radice,</hi> and the womb from whence it ſprings; and that not from a melancholly or ſerous humour; the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is not ſeated <hi>in excrementis,</hi> but in <hi>vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus principiis:</hi> for, as ſanity or health con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in <hi>vita integra;</hi> ſo the Diſeaſe, <hi>in ipſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met vita oblaeſa,</hi> and therefore health and ſickneſs <hi>in eodem hoſpitio vitali degunt,</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively dwell in the ſame Manſion.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ecthius</hi> in his Epitome of the <hi>Scorbute,</hi> deſcribes it thus.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Scorbutus eſt morbus Splenis aliquando ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructi, aliquando intemperati, aliquando cum incipiente Scirro, qui praepedit ejus attractio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ac conſuetant atribilariae redundantiae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrationem, ex hepate veniſque, eoque humore univerſum corpus vitiat, ſed peculiariter craſſiore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30768:15"/>feculentia crura contaminat, atque evaporandae acredine gingivas inficit.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>He ſaith, the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is a Diſeaſe of the Spleen, obſtructed, diſtempered, or hardened, which hinders the attraction and ſeparation of abounding Melancholly from the Liver and veins; by which humour the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is vitiated, the groſſer part affecting the thighs, the thinner acrid part the gums.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A Diſeaſe of the Spleen obſtructed, diſtemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or hardened.]</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here the eſſence of the Diſeaſe is ſet forth and defined, <hi>per effectus ſeparabiles à morbo;</hi> by effects which may, or may not be, and the <hi>Scorbute</hi> in being: and it is abſurd to define a thing eſſentially, by effects which are but reſults <hi>à poſteriori</hi> and ſeparable; and that which is an effect cannot be conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> of the thing from which it doth proceed.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Which hinders the attraction and ſeparation of abounding Melancholly.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Here the <hi>Spleen</hi> is made a place of recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſink, to drain away excrementitious Melancholly from the Liver and Veins: an inferior Office for ſo noble a part; nor is it fabricated or ſituate conveniently for ſuch a uſe; having no ample cavity for recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor a fit paſſage for emiſſion of ſuch an excrement, being intertexed variouſly with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30768:15"/>ſmall veſſels, having inſertions into each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and dores of communication, argues a place of elaboration, and grand affair, not a draught or ſink for venting an excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious humour: if it had been deſtinated for ſo mean ſervice, why was it contrived with ſo many arteries, that no other Part is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd like it, but that it was appointed for higher purpoſes and deſign, and therefore is plentifully ſtock'd and enriched with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirits. More might be ſaid to take off this aſpertion from the <hi>Spleen,</hi> but let this ſuffice at preſent.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Brunerus</hi> in his Tract of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it thus.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Proprie hic morbus eſt affectio lienis, in quo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cervato &amp; leviter putrefacto humore melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico, qui à ſanguine ſeparatus ad lienem tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, pars tenuior ſeu efferveſcens, effertur ſurſum &amp; obſidet gingivas, tanquam tenerrimas oris partes, &amp; putredini maximè obnoxias, eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inficit &amp; erodit, imo etiam emollit: craſſior decumbit ad crura</hi> —</p>
                           <p>He ſaith, this Diſeaſe properly is an effect of the <hi>Spleen;</hi> in which a putrid melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humour is accumulated, ſuparated from the blood and tranſmitted thither.]</p>
                           <p>He makes the <hi>Spleen</hi> to be <hi>ſedes morbi,</hi> the part primarily affected, and yet the peccant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30768:16"/>humour is only tranſmitted thither; and ſo it is but a part recipient, as other parts of the body are; <hi>pars infeſta,</hi> not <hi>primario affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta</hi> from whence it doth ariſe.</p>
                           <p>The thinner part is carried upwards and infects the Gums, the groſſer ſettles down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and affects the Thighs.]</p>
                           <p>This Diſtinction of thicker and thinner parts is frivolous: for, that degenerate <hi>ſcorbutick</hi> Diſpoſition of the Stomach, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the depraved matter lodged there be thick or thin, it will affect the mouth and gums, becauſe the ſtomack and mouth have one membrane lining both the parts; and therfore when the ſtomack is foul, the mouth hath a bad reliſh, and an unſavoury taſt (which is moſt perceived in a morning after digeſtion is paſt;) and let any diſguſtful thing come into the mouth, the ſtomack nauſeates preſently, and is ready to vomit, although it be not ſwallowed down; and this is by reaſon that the mouth and ſtomack have one membrane inveſting both the parts, that the one cannot be affected but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediatly conſents and participates, by reaſon of the continuity of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane; which is more or leſs manifeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greatneſs of the cauſe: So that thickneſs or thinneſs of the matter is not to be taken notice of, but the effect's the ſame be it thick or thin.</p>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30768:16"/>
                           <p>And for that he ſaith, the groſſer part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the thighs, the reaſon is as light as the former, though not to be refelled by the ſame Argument: I ſhall not anticipate my intentions in another place, but refer you to a future opportunity in the diſcourſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, where this point is cleared.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Eugalenus</hi> in his book of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> treats largely of this diſeaſe, in whoſe foot-ſteps moſt Writers ſince have trod, or digreſſing but a little from his opinions, have relied on him as the beſt guide in tracing this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
                           <p>His obſervations are many in his own practice, upon ſeveral perſons variouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with this diſeaſe; and brings in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral infirmities complicated with it, worth your reading.</p>
                           <p>Notwithſtanding the baſis and foundation that he laies, whereon he makes this diſeaſe to be founded, is not firm; and that is <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris Melancholici exuberantia,</hi> abounding Melancholy: to which ſomething hath been ſaid already that I ſhall not repeat, and more to be ſaid in another place, in ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to this error.</p>
                           <p>And in his determination of the internal cauſe and generation of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers his judgment in ambiguous wavering terms, not poſitively and reſolvedly; but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30768:17"/>with ſome kind of diſſatisfaction and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty: his words are theſe, that you may not think I traduce him.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Interna hujus morbi cauſa, melancholici hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris exuberantia cenſetur, ex jam dicta vitae victuſque (ſcilicet inordinati) ratione acquiſita: qui circa lienem &amp; hepar, vel in intermediis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haec &amp; ventriculum ſpatiis, vel in ipſis etiam venis, quod puto, coacervatus; propriam &amp; huic morbo familiarem corruptionis formam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, qua adjacentia, vicinaque viſcera, ſua vel ſubſtantia, &amp; contactu, vel qualitate &amp; fumis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravat, naturalem eorum temperiem corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendo, donec in contagii communionem conſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant:</hi> Where you may obſerve by <hi>cenſetur, vel, puto,</hi> his determination with haeſitation and uncertainty.</p>
                           <p>In finding out the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> for his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſtick ſigns, the Pulſe and Urine are his two great diſcoverers; that in moſt of his Obſervations the one or both confirms his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and relies upon their ſignification: both which are very uncertain; for, there is no particular Pulſe or Urine peculiar to this Diſeaſe, but almoſt all Pulſes and Urins may be in <hi>Scorbutick</hi> perſons, as moſt Diſeaſes may be complicated with it: and therefore their judgment is very fallible and uncertain that depend on theſe ſigns.</p>
                           <p>Others there are who have written Tracts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30768:17"/>of this diſeaſe, as <hi>Ronſſeus, Wierus, Sal. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus, Martinus,</hi> whoſe judgments and opinions are involved and agree in the main, with thoſe already recited; that what hath been ſaid in caſtigation of their errors ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth for theſe, that I need not ſpend time ine xamining them apart: nor have I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted their failings intending their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour (whoſe names I think worthy of memory, for their learning and labours in the medicinal faculty) <hi>humanum eſt errare:</hi> but that it is the duty of every one, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the principles and tenents of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and not ſubſcribe to the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of any, when a clearer light of Reaſon, confirmed by experiments and due obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commands a receſſion from their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practice.</p>
                           <q>Amicus Eugalenus, amicus Sennertus, Sed magis amica veritas.</q>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30768:18"/>
                           <head>Prolegomena.</head>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Induction to the knowledge of the</hi> SCURVY.</head>
                           <p>BEfore I come to define the nature of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> its matter and manner of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and germination, I muſt premiſe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning the Office of digeſtions, for the clearer apprehenſion of what ſhall be thence deductively aſſerted; leſt I taking that for granted, which others in that action or office deny, it will be objected I ſtate my poſitions upon falſe ſuppoſitions, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the baſis of my Reaſons, will think they have ſatisfied the Argument and evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
                           <p>I ſhall therefore ſurvey the digeſtive offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the regularity and irregularity of their actions, defections, and errors, aſſign their cauſes, and draw my concluſions <hi>ad punctum,</hi> to concenter with my intentions and ſcope aimed at.</p>
                           <p>Meat being received into the ſtomack, muſt ſuffer a tranſmutation there in the firſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30768:18"/>laboratory and preparatory Office, for nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of the body: The principal agent in this work, is the ſtomachical ferment; this ferment by its <hi>inciſive acidity penetrates, rarefies &amp; volatiſeth</hi> the food, and tranſmutes it into <hi>Chyle,</hi> or white juce: That which before was fixed, groſs, hard or tough, is made <hi>Volatile, rare</hi> and fluid, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtained that <hi>praevious digeſtion</hi> and perfection proper for that place, the lower orifice of the ſtomack opens and gives it emiſſion, ſending it to the next Office of digeſtion for a new impreſſion.</p>
                           <p>Contrary to this doctrine have the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Phyſitians aſſerted, and built upon, as a ſure foundation, that heat is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal efficient cauſe of digeſtion; being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this opinion, from the ſimilitude of artificial concoctions and digeſtions: And finding humane bodies to be actually hot, ſuppoſed by increaſing of natural heat, to fortifie the digeſtions; and that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of digeſtions in ſeveral perſons, or the ſame perſon at ſeveral times, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend and vary, from the degrees of heat, its debility and fortitude, but upon a due examination you will find it otherwiſe, and from the ſtrength of reaſon be forced to conclude with me thus.</p>
                           <pb n="20" facs="tcp:30768:19"/>
                           <p n="1">1. That heat is a chief agent in the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial preparation and praevious digeſtion of meat, before it be received into the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, whether in roſting, boyling, baking, &amp;c. but not in the natural digeſtions of the body: For, nature in its principal operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons works not primarily by the ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and concomitant effects of life (as heat;) but by vital principles as efficient primitive cauſes.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. That the changing of food into <hi>Chyle</hi> is a fermental tranſmutation from a vital principle, not an impreſſion of a ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate inſtrument.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. That digeſtion in humane bodies, is accompanied with heat, though not the proper effect of heat.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. That internal natural heat by its own power and peculiar efficiency, makes not a digeſtive tranſmutation, but is a conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant of vital operations, contributing <hi>inſtrumentaliter &amp; equivocè</hi> to various effects; and is ſubſervient in the ſeveral digeſtions diſtinct from each other.</p>
                           <p n="5">5. That extraneous and additional heat does excite the vital principles to operation, and is aſiſtant <hi>inſtrumentaliter &amp; excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè,</hi> in performance, <hi>propter ſymbolum quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30768:19"/>
                           <p n="6">6. That heat <hi>quatenus</hi> heat, acts <hi>univocè,</hi> alwaies producing the ſame effects; but as it is the inſtrument of various efficient cauſes, concurs in the production of various heterogene effects; as alſo in reſpect of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers objects upon which it acts.</p>
                           <p n="7">7. That the variety of heat in ſeveral bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are but gradual differences; but diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of digeſtions are from formal diſtinct proprieties.</p>
                           <p n="8">8. That the gradual difference of heat in divers perſons; or in the ſame perſon at ſeveral times, do ſignally teſtifie the ability of the vital principles in their vigour <hi>à pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori,</hi> in their eſſential cauſes; or <hi>à poſteriori</hi> in their manifeſted operations <hi>Claudicari,</hi> to be impedited or depraved accidentally.</p>
                           <p n="9">9. That heat acts not as principle inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally in the ſtomachical digeſtion, but ſubordinately inferior to a ſuperior mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt quality, more immediately the organ of the vital principle or primitive cauſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion: For, heat may be ſufficient, yea, abound, and digeſtion weak or depraved (as in Feavers;) but the other cannot be in its rectitude and vigorous, but the digeſtive faculty muſt be ſtrong and unblamable.</p>
                           <p n="10">10. That veriety of appetites, ſuting with and deſiring ſome kind of meats, but refuſing and rejecting other as diſſentaneous and diſguſtful, ariſeth from the peculiarity
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30768:20"/>and ſingular propriety of ſtomachical fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not the gradual diverſity of heat: For, that which is principal in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is alſo principal in election of the proper object of that faculty, embracing and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what is moſt ſuteable and agreeing, but repugning and ſhewing averſion, from what is diſcordant and diſagreeing, by an innate power and prerogative, as ſupreme modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of that faculty.</p>
                           <p n="11">11. That the digeſtive faculty in fiſhes, being of another region, is not accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with heat; becauſe their vital principles do differ <hi>toto genere</hi> from land <hi>creatures:</hi> And therefore heat is not neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a principal agent, or inſtrument, in digeſtion; but ſhews it ſelf as a diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing character of vitality; yet not vainly or bare ſo, but uſefully where it is.</p>
                           <p>Hence it appears from theſe theſes, with their connexd reaſons, that heat is not the primary efficient cauſe of digeſtion, but an emanative accident, or characteriſtical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant of vital principles, inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſubſervient in the digeſtive faculties; and therefore I muſt reſt upon another baſis, more firm in reaſon, and aſſign a vital principle the parent of digeſtive tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſpecifically diſtinct in every digeſtion: which that you may the better underſtand
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30768:20"/>what they are, I ſhall divide and diſtinguiſh them into theſe following propoſitions.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. That the primary efficient cauſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, is the ferment of that digeſtive Office; which is a vital principle endowed with a tranſmutative power (by way of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude aſtral or influential) diſcharging its vertue upon the object matter to be wrought upon or digeſted.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. That the ſeveral digeſtions have pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar diſtinct ferments, acting ſubordinately in their own ſtations, until aliment be brought to its heigth of perfection, for nutrition of the body.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. That theſe ferments are primitive eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial cauſes, and therefore <hi>à priori</hi> indemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable; but diſcover themſelves <hi>à poſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> in their diſtinct operations and effects.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. That the impreſſions of the ſeveral ferments upon their alimentary objects, are ſo diſtinct that their productive alterations are alien, diſſimilar and oppoſite, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to one ultimate intention, the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and conſervation of the body.</p>
                           <p n="5">5. That the producted alteration of the precedent digeſtion, if not ſubdued &amp; chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſubſequent in its paſſage, is hoſtile, injurious and a morbifick cauſe; if it ſubmit not to the power and government of that Office, through which it hath tranſmiſſion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30768:21"/>by receiving the tranſmutation and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the place: So the <hi>acide cremor</hi> of the firſt digeſtion, is changed into a <hi>ſaline nature</hi> in the ſecond; elſe gripes in the bowels and fluxes do enſue.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. That the emanative influential power of the ferments is abſconded in their cauſes (becauſe vital principles) but detected by aſſuming ſimilar homogeneous manifeſt qualities, ſubſervient to their intentions and inſtrumental in their operations, do ſhew the diverſity of their natures, and what they are.</p>
                           <p n="7">7. That the inſtrumental qualities of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion are indiſpoſed, and unfit, by their intention or remiſſion, being vitiated and depraved from their own natures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties, by improper diſcordant food, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in their natures alienating and hoſtile qualities; or ſimilar qualities in exceſs, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the fermental qualities to a lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uriant injurious exaltation: As pricking and gripes in the ſtomack from <hi>acide juices,</hi> as of lemmons, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p n="8">8. That errors in digeſtion may ariſe from the depravation, enervation and decay of the ferments: or the indiſpoſition of their inſtrumental qualities and organs by which they act; or the intractability, diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy and unfitneſs of the object matter to be wrought upon.</p>
                           <pb n="25" facs="tcp:30768:21"/>
                           <p n="9">9. That the vital Principles, by provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from unnatural bad Cuſtoms, are thruſt and enforced from the conſtancy and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of their operations; thence grow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, debauched and habituated in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the inſtitutions of Nature; do hardly and with difficulty return and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, unleſs coacted by prevalent good means, and regular care for their reduction and reſtoration.</p>
                           <p n="10">10. That the vital principles, without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered or diſturbance, <hi>ab extra,</hi> from injurious bad Cuſtoms and irregular living, do <hi>deficere in radice,</hi> ſpontaneouſly fall off and deſiſt, ſooner or later according to their ſtrength and radication <hi>ab ortu;</hi> in their firſt plantation and initiation: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that ſome in the ordinary courſe of Nature (though irregular in living) do out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and have their faculties perform vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly of longer duration, than ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more regular and conformable to the Laws of Nature; becauſe the difference is great in the Principles of their Nature, and foundation of their beings.</p>
                           <p n="11">11. That <hi>Diaetetick</hi> errors, as in meat and drink, ſleeping and watching, motion and reſt, paſſions of mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do ſo diſcompoſe and diſorder the vital Principles in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their Offices, that their ſtrength
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30768:22"/>and vigour is thereby impoveriſhed and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their duration ſhortned, and haſtens them to a period of extinction: for, as vital Principles are radicated and eſtabliſhed by Nature, ſo are they beſt kept and longeſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, by that courſe and method which Nature hath enjoined for their tuition and conſervation; but being tranſplanted out of their genuine and native regularity, by incongruous and unnatural Cuſtoms, they degenerate, decay, and are of ſhorter dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, much ſooner declining and termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their beings; as more fully is ſet forth in <hi>Tutela Sanitatis,</hi> therefore I forbear here.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>What the Scurvy is, its eſſential con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive Cauſes and manner of Generation.</head>
                           <p>HAving determined the uſe and Office of the digeſtive ferments, their manner of operation, and ſpecifick diſtinction from each other, their divers ſubordinate effects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to one ultimate intention, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſions and durations: which being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and rightly underſtood, the Nature of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> in its Eſſential cauſes and manner of Generation will more cleerly be detected,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30768:22"/>and made obvious to reaſonable capacities: and to facilitate your apprehenſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, to prevent miſtakes or cloudineſs by a long dependant concatenated diſcourſe, I ſhall aphoriſtically deliver my opinions, and divide them into morſels, fit for your recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and more eaſy digeſtion, which you may take thus.</p>
                           <p>Firſt Ngatively.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. It is not one univocal homogeneous preternatural Humour, the <hi>materia ex quae</hi> that generates the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> for as the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms and concomitant Effects are various, ſo is their material cauſe different &amp; various.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. It is not melancholly degenerate and depraved, acquiring a ſpecifick malignity (as moſt <hi>Phyſitians</hi> I meet with in Print do affirm) that is the material cauſe of the <hi>Scurvy:</hi> for <hi>(à ſignis diagnoſticis)</hi> admit there were ſuch a melancholly humour depraved and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fickly malign, this ſpecification would deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it to ſome certainty, and confirm it to ſome diſtinct diagnoſtick ſigns, indubitably declaring its peculiarity and ſeparation from others; for there muſt be ſome ſpecifick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing character which neceſſarily muſt accompany ſuch a ſpecifick malignity; but there is none ſuch, for a man is adjudged to be Scorbutick, with looſeneſs of Teeth and without, with ſpots or without ſpots;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30768:23"/>and ſo likewiſe of the other ſigns, in their abſence and preſence: and the Symptoms are ſo various that they contradict and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn one another in their declarative ſigns, that they own diſtinct cauſes not one pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar malignity.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, The diverſity or difference of the ſcorbutick ſpots do argue variation of the material cauſe, and not one Specifick malign humour: for, if you judge of temperaments by colours, making them one ſort of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Characters, (as you do) ſaying this perſon is Phlegmatick, becauſe pale; and that ſanguine, becauſe roſy; and this cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick, of paliſh yellow: as alſo of preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tumors, ſaying, this is a <hi>Phlegmone,</hi> that <hi>Eryſipilas,</hi> or <hi>oedema, &amp;c.</hi> from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of their colours and external appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, aſſigning ſeveral humours and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of humours for cauſes; then why not various commaculations and diſcolou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in parts, as well as various extubera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhould challenge divers material cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſince they differ but <hi>ratione quantitatis,</hi> in the quantity of peccant matter, the one hath more, the other leſs; and ſometimes theſe ſpots do germinate and ſwell into Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick tumors <hi>ex abundanti materia,</hi> from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the ſame depraved matter, and have their variations and denominations as other preternatural tumors have.</p>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:30768:23"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A juvantibus &amp; contra.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>If melancholy humour be the foundation of this Diſeaſe, then Purgatives that attract melancholly (as you ſuppoſe) would prevent this Diſeaſe, or eradicate it; but you may purge and purge Spring and Fall, and yet the <hi>Scurvy</hi> ſhall come on and prevail: but if it be melancholly degenerate &amp; malign, as you ſay, then ſudorificks would be the grand oppoſers of this Diſeaſe; but neither Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives or Sudorificks, nor both, are the ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate medicines of this Diſeaſe, yet both uſeful <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> applied to the Effects and Products of it: but that which unhingeth this Diſeaſe, ſtops the ſpring, prevents or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radicates it, roborates the faculties intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and primarily, reſtores them to integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and priſtine vigour in the performance of their Functions and duties.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A Cauſis antecedentibus externis:</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Certain Climates, Regions and bad Airs are procuring and promoting Cauſes of this Diſeaſe; not that we can imagine they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender melancholly more than other places, but becauſe they are infeſted with noxious fumes and vapours, which ſurrounding and being drawn into the body, commix with the Spirits, and do <hi>labefactare vitae principia,</hi> debilitate and deprave the faculties in their operations, from whence Scorbutick effects do enſue.</p>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:30768:24"/>
                           <p>But you may ſay, a ſedentary, ſtudious and melancholly Life does often breed the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> and therefore it muſt needs be a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly humour, the material Cauſe &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this Diſeaſe: To which I anſwer; that a melancholly inactive Life does breed the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> but how? not to conclude from thence that it is a melancholly humour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and malign; but becauſe by ſuch a condition of Life the vital Principles do receive much prejudice, decay and fall off from their Functions; for mirth and an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Life do roborate all the faculties, keeps them vigorous, the Spirits being chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; lively in the performance of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but by the contrary are languid, debile and inſufficient, from whence many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences and prejudices to the body do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, as you may ſee enumerated in that Book called <hi>Tutela Sanitatis.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But you may farther ſay, the <hi>Spleen</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeat of that paſſion, is chiefly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and injured thereby, and therefore it muſt needs be a Splenetick luxuriant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
                           <p>That a melancholly Life does debilitate and fruſtrate the <hi>Spleen</hi> in the rectitude of its Office, I agree, and not the <hi>Spleen</hi> only, but other principal parts and Offices of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion alſo; for if melancholly ſeiz and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30768:24"/>fix the Spirits, makes them torpid (as it is the property of it ſo to do) and the Spirits are principal agents in all the faculties, then not the <hi>Spleen</hi> only is prejudiced, and a ſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick humour only that abounds, but all parts do participate of the injury idiopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thically; and all the digeſtions are vitiated, and their ill effects do appear Scorbutical, and variouſly complicated as their ſeveral Actions and Offices are various.</p>
                           <p>Having ſhewed you Negatively, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined that the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is not what ſome have ſuppoſed it to be; I ſhall now poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſet down what it is, in theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Theorems.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is generated by the conjunction or conſpiration of divers Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; yet disjunct in their cauſation, ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately and diſtinctly contributing to a Scorbutick difformity; for, although the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the firſt digeſtion lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it is not compleated ſo as to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the denomination of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til by addition from the irregularity and depravedneſs of other parts.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is a complication or concatenation of Diſeaſes, conſpiring to the making up of its difformity and <hi>Prothean</hi> ſhapes; not ariſing from a ſingle Diſeaſe, or any ſolitary cauſe: for, as the variety of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30768:25"/>ſymptoms and products do appear in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts, diſſimilar and unlike, being the effects of ſeveral inordinate faculties; muſt of neceſſity Challenge and own diſtinct im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate cauſes, as the parts wherein thoſe faculties do reſide, are diſtinct and ſeparate in place and Office.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. That the difformity of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> in the diverſity and diſſimilarity of ſymptoms, ariſeth from the complication of errors in the digeſtions, and variety of parts thereby affected and drawn into conſent.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. That the individual variegation of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> ariſeth from the peculiar aſſociation of cauſes, and <hi>idioſyncratical</hi> propriety of particular perſons, producing ſuch and ſuch ſymptoms, which in no other perſon you will exactly find the like: For, as ſound bodies in reſpect of ſanity having a parallel equality and proportion in the whole; yet particularly and disjunctively collated there is great variety and difference; in ſtature organization, complexion, inclinations, appetitions, performance of functions, &amp;c. If there be ſuch variety of parts, proprieties, and operations in humane bodies in a ſtate of ſanity and integrity which is uniform: then much more variety and diſproportion in a ſtate of declenſion and irregularity, which is deform and multiform.</p>
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:30768:25"/>
                           <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is generated <hi>formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; eſſentialiter,</hi> in the vital principles <hi>ut ens inviſibile,</hi> not diſcerned by ſence: But the effects and products are diſtributed, have their reſidence in all the parts, and are ſenſitive objects; as ſpots, pains, looſneſs of <hi>Teeth,</hi> putrid <hi>Gums, Tumors, ulcers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is planted <hi>Seminaliter &amp; radicaliter</hi> in the digeſtions or digeſtive Offices, whoſe ramifications, ſpread through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the body, and are increaſed <hi>extenſivè,</hi> more or leſs, according to the fortitude and debility of parts, to reſiſt or conſent and be depraved.</p>
                           <p n="7">7. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> increaſeth, or is worſe <hi>intenſivè,</hi> from the greater fruſtration of digeſtions and degeneration of the digeſtive matter, <hi>ex cauſis antecedentibus quibuſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="8">8. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is procured <hi>occaſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter,</hi> by numerous and various <hi>diaetetick acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental cauſes,</hi> ſeducing the vital principles to declenſion and deviation from their rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and integrity.</p>
                           <p n="9">9. That the <hi>ratio formalis,</hi> quiddity and eſſence of the <hi>Scurvey</hi> is defection and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the vital principles; occaſionally procured <hi>ab extra</hi> &amp; moved to ſuch a devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Or ſpontaneouſly inclining through
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30768:26"/>an innate deficiency and hereditary propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; or natural inability, longer to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, from the fragility of conſtitutive prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in nature.</p>
                           <p n="10">10. That the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is not reſtrained to any certain ſymptomes either in quantity or quality; or univocal material cauſe: But is various and equivocal as to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial products, by degeneration and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; as alſo unlimited in the ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</p>
                           <p n="11">11. That the part affected <hi>principaliter,</hi> cheifly and contributing <hi>prae aliis,</hi> to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and deformity of this diſeaſe, is the <hi>Spleen.</hi> For that the <hi>Spleen</hi> is a principal member, in chylification, and ſanguificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as to perfection and conſervation; and by a deficiency in the <hi>Spleen,</hi> both are vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there wanting due fermentation: and therefore the <hi>Spleen</hi> is fabricated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived with ſo many arteries, having plenty of ſpirits for this office.</p>
                           <p n="12">12. That <hi>Scorbute</hi> ſpots ariſe from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment, vitiation, or extinction of the laſt digeſtion, or aſſimilation; and that <hi>ratione ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecti deturpati: vel facultatis tranſmutativae deficientis:</hi> Either the alimentary object is depraved and unfit; or the aſſimilating fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is languid, deficient or extinct.</p>
                           <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30768:26"/>
                           <p n="13">13. That ſpots appear chiefly upon the Thighs, and Leggs, not from the gravity of their material cauſe &amp; ponderous propenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of groſſer matter downwards, as is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly alledged for the reaſon; but becauſe ignoble parts are more weak &amp; debile in their aſſimilation, being more remote from aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance &amp; ſupply of vital ſpirits, have firſt the tokens of defection: And farther, not the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er parts only are ſo affected, but the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or parts frequently, as Arms and Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, from the ſame cauſe, do bear the ſame characters, not diſtinguiſhable by tenuity and groſſneſs of humor.</p>
                           <p n="14">14. That Scorbutick pains are cauſed from alien qualities ariſing out of the degenerate matter in the parts ſo moleſted; or from ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machical acidity tranſmitted unſubdued; from defect or debility of the ſecond digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or its own luxuriant exorbitancy reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſmutation and obedience in its paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
                           <p n="15">15. That <hi>pro ratione corporis perſpirabilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, plus minuſve, ſcorbutus variatur:</hi> As the body is perſpirable or impervious more or leſs, is the <hi>Scurvy</hi> varied, intended and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the ſymptoms: And therefore the Craſſities, impenitration of the skin, and conſtipation of the pores, prohibiting tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration, is a partial organical cauſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30768:27"/>ſpots, and makes for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and duration: For, as the body in its natural good ſtate is tranſpirable, giving emiſſion to what is ſuperfluous remaining after the laſt digeſtion; on the contrary, the reſtraint thereof by congeſtion, begets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculations and defaedations of the skin, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and apoſtumations, one or other, <hi>pro magnitudine cauſarum.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="16">16. That although the <hi>Scurvy, eo nomine,</hi> is not of long ſtanding, and unknown to the ancient Phyſitians under that title, and the diſtinguiſhing characters that we denote it by; yet the diſeaſe <hi>in ſpecie</hi> is antique, though <hi>in individuis</hi> not ſo frequently then, nor perhaps characterized altogether alike, as we now diſtinguiſh it: For, as humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies do decline in theſe latter daies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from the priſtine vigour of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients in all the faculties and abilities of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by reaſon of intemperance, and various manners of abuſive living, tranſmitted <hi>in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> from generation to generation; ſo likewiſe, and for theſe cauſes, diſeaſes do not continue alike and certain, but have their variations, and complications different; which occaſions new names, though the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe be the ſame in its eſſential conſtitutive cauſes and manner of generation.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="37" facs="tcp:30768:27"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Preſervation from the</hi> Scurvy, <hi>and to be obſerved in the</hi> Scurvy.</head>
                           <p>IN the due Regiment of Health, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from Diſeaſes; you muſt conſider and know that all things which belong, and are neceſſary for the preſervation of the body and ſupport of Nature; that they alſo may be the antecedent procuring cauſes of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as alſo the fomenting and aggravating cauſes of diſeaſes already generated: as when contrary to the law or diſpoſition of our peculiar Natures, they are applied or uſed unſeaſonably, immoderately, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſly, or any waies unſutably to our Nature and Condition of Body: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both in the time of preſervation and curation they are to be regarded.</p>
                           <p>And ſince there is not a moment of time in which we do not ſtand in need of air; and that being conſtantly drawn into the body, muſt needs make for, or againſt the continuance of health, according to the conditions and properties it is pregnant with.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore in preſervation from the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> it is of no ſmall concernment the air and climate that you live in, to diſpoſe or defend you from it: the nature of the air is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30768:28"/>ſuch in ſome places, that few there are not tainted with it, and this as a principal cauſe. And therefore in <hi>Holland, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and ſuch places this diſeaſe is moſt common; and chiefly in the Fenny and Marriſh parts: for that a moiſt foggy cold air is apt to ingender this diſeaſe or increaſe it: becauſe the ſpirits thereby are clogged and fixed, dull and inactive; from whence defects in fermentation, humors incraſſated and obſtructions, the pores occluded, and tranſpiration prohibited.</p>
                           <p>But a warm, drie, ſerene air makes much in the preſervation from the <hi>Scurvy:</hi> the ſpirits thereby are kept more vigorous, live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and brisk; humors attenuated, volatile, and freely circulating; the pores more open and perſpirable, giving emiſſion to excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious vapours unprofitable and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be reſtrained; and all the parts more free in their communications and ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency one to the other.</p>
                           <p>Thoſe that retire themſelves voluntarily to a ſtudious ſedentary life, or are confined to a cloſe chamber airy, are thereby diſpoſed to this diſeaſe; or much aggravated and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, if already they are ſcorbutick, more ſpecially if melancholy be their companion: and where the air is impure, not to be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as in great Cities, correct it ſomthing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30768:28"/>by Art in your houſes, with wholſom fumes, eſpecially in moiſt cold weather: They that live in Cities, eſpecially ſome parts thereof, more cloſe and noiſom than others; as in narrow ſtreets, lanes and Allies, are much prejudiced in their health. There is great difference in the place and parts of a City to live in; the broader ſtreets and places more open and airy, the wholſomer: and the outſide <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> near the freſh fields is better than to be crouded in the middle, provided no ſtinking ditches or dunghils be adjacent.</p>
                           <p>And here I cannot but take notice of <hi>Bloomsbury</hi> (the Right Honourable Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi>'s propriety and Seat) for the beſt part about <hi>London,</hi> both for health and pleaſure exceeding other places: It is the beſt air and fineſt proſpect, being the higheſt ground, and overlooking other parts of the City. The fields bordering upon this place are very pleaſant, and drie grounds, for walking and improving of health; a fit place for Nobility and Gentry to reſide in, that make their abode about <hi>London;</hi> there being the Country air, pleaſure, and City conveniencies joined together: Now lately improved and built upon, and ſtill encreaſing with fair and well contrived Buildings, a good addition, and Ornament to this place.</p>
                           <pb n="40" facs="tcp:30768:29"/>
                           <p>The next conſiderable in a regular preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> is Diet; which ought to be duly obſerved: for, as by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient food, ſutable and agreeable in all the requiſite circumſtances, quantity, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, time, and order: ſo on the contrary, by a diſproportionate and unſutable diet, the faculties are diſordered and debilitated in their ſeveral functions, inclining to this or that diſeaſe, according to the nature and quality of the food, and other circumſtances that attend it.</p>
                           <p>And therefore ſome kind of meats and drinks do diſpoſe, and are the antecedent cauſes of this diſeaſe; as alſo do cheriſh and help to maintain it where it is already ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, although procured firſt by other cauſes.</p>
                           <p>The groſſer meats, and ſuch as do not eaſily digeſt are to be avoided; but light meats, and ſuch as the ſtomack does well agree with, covet, and digeſt beſt, keep to ſuch.</p>
                           <p>Milk and Milk-meats in a foul body do ſoon alter and degenerate, and therefore injurious to Scorbutick Perſons; but in clean bodies 'tis good food.</p>
                           <p>Broom buds, Capers and Sampire are good ſauce to your meate, helps the Stomack in digeſtion, and is profitable for the Spleen;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30768:29"/>a part chiefly affected in the <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Alſo Oranges and Lemmons, Berberries and Sorrel helps fermentation, and are good.</p>
                           <p>But old fleſh, drie and hard meats long kept, Rie-bread, and brown, eſpecially Cruſts, fried, or broyled meats, are to be avoided: for theſe are more ſtubborn, do not ſoon yield to fermentation, nor beget good nutriment: as alſo ſalt fiſh, and meats ſmoak-dried, as hang'd Bief, Bacon, dried Tongues, and ſuch like, are injurious, and promote this diſeaſe: But for variety of meats and their qualities you may ſee a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue in my <hi>Tutela Sanitatis,</hi> therefore I ſhall not repeat them here.</p>
                           <p>For Drinks take theſe obſervations:</p>
                           <p>Drink not your Beer new, becauſe not yet fully purified by fermentation, but rather ſtale, well hop'd, clear, &amp; reaſonable ſtrong, if your ſtomack be weak and declining.</p>
                           <p>And it is very conſiderable, of what wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your drink is made; for that there is great variety and difference in the goodneſs of waters, being impregnated with ſeveral qualities from the nature of earth through which it paſſeth; and ſeveral accidents that happen to change water from its genuine properties, and make it impure and unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, by carrion, filth, and ſuch like admix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that may corrupt it.</p>
                           <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30768:30"/>
                           <p>And from theſe cauſes many places are more diſpoſed to breed the <hi>Scurvy</hi> than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from bad water with which their Beer or Ale is made, and meats dreſſed. And <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> relates, that <hi>Caeſars</hi> Army by drinking of bad water but a few daies, had the ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of the <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Ale I do not approve of; but white Wine and Rheniſh is good for you to drink a glaſs or two ſomtimes, to open obſtructions, cleanſe and whet the appetite, and promote fermentation.</p>
                           <p>Sider alſo is good drink, if it be made of the beſt Apples; as Pippins, Pearmains, and ſuch like; and that it be clear, having had good time to ferment, ſeparate, and purifie: but withall have reſpect to your ſtomack, that it be agreeable, and deſired by it: but if you have a cold, raw ſtomack, a warmer liquor will be more acceptable; as a glaſs of Canary ſomtimes, to fortifie the ſtomack and help digeſtion, is agreeable to the moſt.</p>
                           <p>The next conſiderable for praecaution of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> is exerciſe and motion: which duly and moderately uſed, is a good preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative from this diſeaſe: a ſedentary ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful life makes the body to degenerate from its purity and vigour. <hi>Corrumpunt otia corpus.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="43" facs="tcp:30768:30"/>
                           <p>From hence Defects in fermentation, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours incraſſate and obſtruct; the Spirits being torpid, dull and inactive, do not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify and circulate the blood, as when by motion they are excited and ſtirred up to their duties and performances: by ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exerciſe the digeſtions are ſtrengthened, obſtructions opened, and evacuations more duly performed: and ſince an idle Life doth procure and promote this Diſeaſe, you muſt account it as your enemy to avoid it.</p>
                           <p>And like to this is the indulging of ſleep unſeaſonably, beyond its limits and due times; from whence neceſſary evacuations are reſtrained and put by their due accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed times; and ſuperfluous humours ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated and lodged, that otherwiſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would have ſent forth profitably in good time; the ſpirits are made ſluggiſh, dull and inactive, and all the faculties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured.</p>
                           <p>But on the contrary, let not watching ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed its juſt times appointed by Nature; for from hence the inconveniencies are as great; eſpecially to ſuch bodies as are lean and ſpare, or inclining to be Conſumptive and hectical; by over-watching the ſpirits are heated and tyred, the bloud degenerates and turns acrid or ſharp, leaving its balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30768:31"/>nature, and is diſpoſed to a colliquati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſeparation of parts; the vigour of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is hereby abated, and the functions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved.</p>
                           <p>Paſſions of mind, though in the laſt place accounted, are not the leaſt, but principally to be regarded, and due order to be kept there for preſervation from infirmities: for the Soul being the better and more noble part, from whoſe command and power bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily actions do proceed; of neceſſity if that be diſcompoſed and diſordered, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental part muſt act irregularly and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly; and of all the Paſſions, melancholly and ſadneſs do moſt diſpoſe to this Diſeaſe, and aggravate it; the reaſons are theſe.</p>
                           <p>The Soul in that Paſſion ſuſpends and withdraws her influence and emanative ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which was wont to be enlarged and let forth into all the faculties, mediately by the ſpirits, her chief and appropriate Agents; and the Soul in this ſtate and condition of ſadneſs, being as it were lock'd up and ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within her ſelf, darkened and overſpread with a cloud of melancholly, does not <hi>emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere &amp; emanare,</hi> ſend forth her wonted quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power; by which ſuſpenſion the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are diſpoſed to ceſſation from their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereby the faculties are enervated and deficient in their functions.</p>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:30768:31"/>
                           <p>The <hi>Spleen</hi> which is accounted the ſeat of this Paſſion, is chiefly debilitated and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited in its office; the ſpirits hereby are fixed and deaded, fermentation cohibited and reſtrained, from whence <hi>ſcorbutick</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects do enſue; for that by the benefit of fermentation, our food is decocted, deſerts its crudity and fixity; is raiſed and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a ſtate of volatility, that it may be fit for nutrition, and aſſimilation into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the body: but if fermentation be deficient and wanting, neither chylification nor ſanguification can be good, but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depraved and vitiated.</p>
                           <p>But concerning the ſeveral Paſſions of mind, and their various effects wrought in the body, is ſet forth in that book called <hi>Tutela Sanitatis,</hi> to which I refer the Reader for ſatisfaction.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>Determinations of the Scurvy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the difficulty and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of the Cure.</head>
                           <p>BEfore I enter upon diſcourſe of the Cure, to lay down fundamental precepts, and rules upon which it does depend; I ſhall ſay ſomething as to the poſſibility of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30768:32"/>Cure in particular perſons, in whom there is a great difference; that by examination every one may give a rational conjecture of their own condition and ſtate in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; and be ſomething ſatisfied of the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty or facility of their Cure before they undertake the Courſe, and method to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it.</p>
                           <p>Many there are more curious and inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to know what their Diſeaſe is, how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and whether curable, than they will be induſtrious afterwards for a Cure: If it be the beginning of a Diſeaſe, and not very troubleſome, they contemn and ſlight it: if it be of long ſtanding and difficult to deal with, they deſpond and have no hopes to part, being ſo long aſſociated together; and then give themſelves the liberty of their phancies in the diſcipline and order of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whether it be good or bad, for or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Diſeaſe.</p>
                           <p>Others more rational in their actions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a ſatisfaction concerning the nature and radication of their Diſeaſes, and ſtate of their bodies, that they may order them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the beſt advantage, and to oppoſe their Diſeaſe with that ſtrictneſs and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, in the uſe of good means, as is thought requiſite for ſuch a cure.</p>
                           <p>In ſatisfaction to ſuch which are ſcorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30768:32"/>that you may know in what condition you are, and the ſtrength of your Diſeaſe, and what poſſibility of Cure, whether diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult or more eaſy: Examine your ſelf by theſe queſtions.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. What Functions in the body are decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and irregular, more or fewer; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch faculties ſo injured be principal or of a lower degree: for, according to the number of Functions diſordered and debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, is your Diſeaſe better or worſe: and if they be from principal faculties the worſe alſo: therefore look to the diſtinguiſhing Characters that belong to each faculty, which will declare whether they perform re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, or diſorderly and dificiently: the Characters of rectitude are the common ſigns, when every part performs its Office according to the cuſtom of Nature: the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of declenſion and a depraved condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are all ſuch as declare the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. The duration and time, how long ſuch ſymptoms and ſigns hath appeared and been manifeſt; for by how much the longer this Diſeaſe hath been rooted in the body, by ſo much the more difficult it is to be eradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for that the vital principles have ſo long deviated from their rectitude and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and is more difficult to return, by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30768:33"/>the length of time habituated to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The <hi>Scurvy</hi> in the beginning is of eaſy cure, and ſoon yields to gentle medicines, properly appointed, with due orderly Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms; but after it is fixed and radicated firmly by time, ſtamping impreſſions of its depraved Nature upon all the Parts, is then more ſtubborn and difficult to be removed, and will require more time in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt, although with effectual medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. Whether the <hi>Scurvy</hi> be haereditary; that is, deſcended of <hi>ſcorbutick</hi> Parents, or their Anceſtors: and here you muſt know, that the <hi>Scurvy</hi> haereditarily derived, is worſe than that which is acquired by ill dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, bad air, melancholly and unwholſom cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms: for, if the <hi>Scurvy</hi> be worſe and more difficult to be removed in thoſe habituated to it, by length of time, acquired only by a declenſion and degeneration; then much more when it is radicated in the principles of Nature from the birth, and derived from their Parents or Anceſtors, it being then connatural to them <hi>à principio.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="4">4. What Sex, Male or Female: the Sex makes ſome difference in the facility or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of a Cure; it being worſe in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are more obnoxious to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of this diſeaſe than men.</p>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:30768:33"/>
                           <p>Firſt, becauſe they are of a weaker na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, more apt to degenerate and accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ill humors; whoſe conſtitutions are ſooner changed, being more expoſed by ſuch a feminine debility; not ſo able to reſiſt the procuring and occaſional cauſes of this Diſeaſe, as maſculine vigour, and fortitude of their vital principles.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, by reaſon of their accuſtomed courſes in Nature which are apt to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, decreaſed, qualitatively altered, or be diſordered in time, that Nature hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purgation, which brings much detriment; and this happens to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from ſmall occaſions ſometimes; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially infirm and diſeaſed bodies, which ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates and promotes their other infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or inclinations to ſuch.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of Child-bearing and the weakneſſes that attend ſuch a condition, which decay and abate their vigour and ſtrength; and in the time of their going with Child the <hi>Scurvy</hi> doth prevail very much; partly for ſome of the preceding reaſons; as alſo that in ſuch a condition they cannot ſo well oppoſe the Diſeaſe by that Diſcipline &amp; order as is required: and ſeveral I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to die in Child-bed by <hi>ſcorbutic</hi> Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and ſome ſuffocated ſoon after a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable good delivery, by a ſudden and great
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30768:34"/>fermentation, occaſioned from the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Labour, and extraordinary internal motions.</p>
                           <p>4ly. In giving judgment of this Diſeaſe, the age of the perſon is to be conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in young or old: in old age the cure is more difficult by how much the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becauſe the vital principles are declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their vigour, and fall off from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and rectitude of their Natures ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly, from their proneneſs to deſiſt, and natural inability to a longer duration; and therefore are not to be reſtored, but may be retarded in their ſpeed of declenſion; their ill affects corrected and abated, not wholly prevented, being the inevitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of lapſed Nature.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>Scurvy</hi> in Children argues an haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary infirmity derived from their Parents, or the vital principles debile and weak in their initiation and plantation: or that their Nurſes were ſcorbutical, and tainted with this infirmity, from whom the child hath imbibed and drawn in impure nutriment, to corrupt the principles of its Nature in the in fancy and tender daies, being then more apt to receive, and longer to retain any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <hi>quo ſemel eſt imbuta.</hi> —</p>
                           <p>In all theſe Cauſes the difficulty of the Cure is advanced; and ſince ſo great a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30768:34"/>may ariſe to Infants from their Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, therefore there ought to be a ſtrict and diligent care in the choice of them, and that by the approbation of an able Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian before the Infant is committed to them.</p>
                           <p>5ly. The colour of <hi>ſcorbutick</hi> ſpots declaring this Diſeaſe, is to be regarded; for that ſuch ſpots by how much they encline to black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo much the worſe: denoting a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter degeneration of the material product, or extinction of the aſſimulating faculty.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Quicquid eſt in effectu, praeexiſtit in cauſa;</hi> arguing the vital principles to be very enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and deficient; or the <hi>materia ex qua</hi> and nutrimental object to be of a very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Nature, not to be reduced.</p>
                           <p>6ly. That the Cure is more difficult and will be longer in effecting to thoſe that are irregular, live high, looſe and careleſs; not obſerving laudable Cuſtoms, and ſuch a Diſcipline as is required to oppoſe the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe: as alſo to ſuch, whoſe low condition and inability, conſtrains them to a bad dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, inconveniencies and ill cuſtoms which promote and aggravate this Diſeaſe alſo.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="52" facs="tcp:30768:35"/>
                           <head>The Therapeutick or Curative part examined.</head>
                           <p>THe common method in curing this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, is carried on by theſe intentions: preparation of the ſcorbutick matter; open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of obſtructions; evacuation of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick cauſe; and roboration of parts.</p>
                           <p>For the firſt intention namely Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is performed (as they ſuppoſe) by medicaments that are attenuating and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive, and by a more peculiar property do reſpect the malignant Cauſe: and ſuch me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines are compounded of theſe ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, <hi>Fumiterry, Spleenwort, Germander, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chory, Borrage, Bugloſs, Harts-tongue, Enula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane, Squils, Bark</hi> of <hi>Tamarisk, Cappar roots, Polipody, &amp;c.</hi> Of which decoctions are made, and drank ſome daies before purging, to prepare the morbifick humor, and make it more fit for evacuation.</p>
                           <p>That ſome of theſe rightly uſed are good againſt the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> I do not deny, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of preparation is a deluſion of judgment: Firſt, becauſe there is no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of reducing this degenerate ſcorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick matter into a good ſtate and condition,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30768:35"/>
                              <hi>à privatione ad habitum non datur regreſſus. Ax.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Secondly, for that the humour which you intend ſo to prepare, is occult and unknown in its proprieties (by your own determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;) the preparation then is but a blind buſineſs, and a ſhooting at random.</p>
                           <p>Thirdly, for that there is no purgative which attracts <hi>electivè</hi> this humour you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thus to prepare: wherefore no prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is available or beneficial, diſtinct from that which is antiſcorbutical and cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
                           <p>The ſecond intention is opening of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and that is neceſſarily included in antiſcorbutical medicines, which are a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritive, rarifying, volatiſing and of a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Nature: but if it be meant only as a praevious diſpoſition to the Cure, I think it more nicely diſtinguiſhed, than neceſſary to be obſerved.</p>
                           <p>The third intention is evacuation of the morbifick cauſe; and that is ſuppoſed to be performed by phlebotomy and purgation.</p>
                           <p>Phlebotomy I cannot approve of (except there be a <hi>plethora</hi> urging) for that this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is generated and depends upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of fermentation; which rather requires addition of ſpirits to help the laſſated <hi>vires,</hi> exciting and aſſiſting their wonted operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30768:36"/>not detraction and diminution: but <hi>hirudines venis haemorrhoidalibus appoſitae</hi> for ſome perſons may be profitable.</p>
                           <p>It fares with the Bloud, as in other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors; when their ſpirits are gone, flat and dead, they change their former nature and degenerate; and all things that exhauſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs or fix the Spirits, are promoters of this Diſeaſe: and I much wonder Phlebotomy ſo frequently uſed upon ſlight occaſions, perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſometimes and mortally; as in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the ſmall Pox, more apparently, at ſuch time when the bloud is fermenting for a purification; detraction of blood then abates the ſtrength of Nature, by emiſſion of ſpirits; which ceaſeth the ebullition, and checks Nature in the very height of conteſt, for expulſion of the malignity and virulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Diſeaſe, but this <hi>obitèr.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Purgation is appointed to be performed by ſuch medicines as evacuate melancholly, ſuppoſing that predominant humour to be the cauſe of this Diſeaſe; but if I ſhould grant melancholly to be the morbifick cauſe, and that purgatives do attract <hi>electivè;</hi> yet the proceſs of the cure is not rationally grounded; for that this melancholly (as you ſay) is degenerate and changed from its ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick known nature, into that which is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and unknown; metamorphoſed and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30768:36"/>diſguiſed by occult proprieties, ariſing from its ſecret and new Nature: ſo that it is not the ſame, but another humour diſtinct from what it was before: and now you muſt ſeek for another Purger, peculiar and different from the common Purgers of melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                           <p>And farther, here is a great miſtake in taking that to be the morbifick cauſe, which is the morbifick effect: that excrementiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matter which is purged out, is but the product or effect of the Diſeaſe, not the cauſe; except it be occaſional; not eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and conſtitutive.</p>
                           <p>You muſt diſtinguiſh between the Diſeaſe and the product thereof: depraved matter and excrements are the products of a Diſeaſe, and may be the internal occaſional cauſes of another Diſeaſe: but in reſpect of the Diſeaſe of which they are ſo a cauſe, they are external; that is, they are not the conſtitutive eſſential cauſes: for <hi>Cauſae conſtitntivae &amp; conſtitutum ſunt ſimul in eſſe:</hi> but occaſional cauſes are antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and have priority of exſtience; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the product matter or effect is diſtinct and ſeparate from the Diſeaſe; for that the Diſeaſe hath a real exiſtence before ſuch a production; and alſo after this degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate matter is removed, unleſs otherwiſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30768:37"/>obliterated; or that Nature <hi>ſua ſponte</hi> returns to her integrity and rectitude.</p>
                           <p>The laſt intention is Roboration, which is the perfection of the Cure, and praecaution for the future; and this is ſo neceſſary, that although the Diſeaſe make a ceſſation for a time, yet there will be a recidivation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence: the parts being debilitated by the pravity of this Diſeaſe, will ſhew their propenſion to it; until thoſe impreſſions be totally obliterated, and the parts reſtored to their priſtine vigour.</p>
                           <p>And this is not performed by dyet-drinks, Apozems, Syrups, and ſuch like heterogene languid medicines; but with ſuch as are purely defaecated from terenity, volatized, ſpiritallized, and graduated to a pitch of energy, ſymphoniacal with vital princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
                           <p>Having briefly diſcourſed the ſcope and intentions of the common method in the Cure of this Diſeaſe; I ſhall now give you ſome <hi>Theſes curative,</hi> deducted from the Theorical part of this work, founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Doctrine delivered.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. That the difficulty in curing the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> does depend upon the principal cauſes in the digeſtive and diſtributive faculties, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more or leſs enervated, deficient or ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular; not from the contumacy of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30768:37"/>humor (as is alleaged;) for, as the vitioſity and difformity of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> does ariſe from the complicated defection of the digeſtive and diſtributive faculties; ſo the difficulty alſo, or facility of the Cure does depend upon the poſſibility of reſtoration to their integrity and rectitude: and if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal conſtitutive cauſes of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> be cut off and ſubdued, the ſymptoms and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that from thence do depend, will ſoon die and vaniſh, not being ſupplyed by their cauſes of generation and conſervation: therefore it is not the contumacy of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted degenerate matter that protracts, or makes the Diſeaſe incurable, but the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of reducing the vital principles to their integrity and rectitude, being weakly or depravedly radicated, or habituated to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormity and irregularity, enforced by diaete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick bad Cuſtoms; or promoted and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by ſome unavoidable occaſional cauſe.</p>
                           <p n="2">2ly. That an haereditary <hi>ſcorbutick</hi> diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to be changed and altered in the radication; but will ſhew a propenſion and inclination ſuiting with the peculiarity of its Nature and principles: for, Nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved <hi>à principio in principiis,</hi> is not to be reduced, but will retain her vitioſity being indiviſible and inſeparable from her ſelf; nor is capable of reduction, having
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30768:38"/>not had the principles of rectitude to return to.</p>
                           <p n="3">3ly. That an haereditary Scorbutick diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fition as to fructification and ſymptomati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal production, may be prevented, retarded, or leſſened; for that the ſymptoms and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts which uſually attend this diſeaſe, are under the command, and muſt give obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a diaetetick and pharmaceutick pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority.</p>
                           <p n="4">4ly. That the various ſymptomatical ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Scurvy, and difference of ſcorbutick matter by degeneration in divers perſons, does not alwaies neceſſarily require variety of Medecines, but will admit the ſame cure; for, although in the production &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the diſeaſe, there is great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yet there is more certainty and unity in the eſſential conſtitutive cauſes, the ſpring or fountain from whence thoſe iſſue; to which rightly applied the cure will ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, <hi>reliquum ſupplente natura juvata.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="5">5ly. That the occaſional, or antecedent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal cauſes of this diſeaſe, by way of prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution; or the product matter and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of this diſeaſe, <hi>in primis viis</hi> ſeated, may conveniently be removed by manifeſt eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation: that is degenerate <hi>Chyle,</hi> which will not be reduced, but deprave and infeſt where it reſides, paſſes, and is tranſmitted;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30768:38"/>yet the ſpirits and ferments are chiefly to be regarded, that they be kept in their purity and vigor, being the principles in each fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; and this is performed <hi>privativè,</hi> by ſubducting what is offenſive and injurious; and alſo <hi>poſitivè,</hi> by contributing an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal ſtrength, having ſome equality or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ſuting with their natures.</p>
                           <p n="6">6ly. That purgation cannot eradicate, or take away the conſtitutive cauſes of this diſeaſe; but only carry off ſome of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted ſcorbutick matter, which is not redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, and is <hi>remedium à poſteriori:</hi> for, the eſſential conſtitutive cauſes of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> are enormity and deficiency of the vital princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in their duties; which are to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to their regularity and fortitude: but evacuation <hi>per ſe</hi> reſpects the producted mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and effects, not the eſſential cauſes, but <hi>per accidens:</hi> and therefore that which does apply radically to the internal cauſes of this diſeaſe is ſymbolical and conſimilar with the vital principles, uniting with them, roborating and confirming them in their functions; and therefore they that lay all the ſtreſs of the cure upon evacuation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purging, vomiting, bleeding, or ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as if that alone muſt do it, are much deceived and fruſtrated in their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                           <pb n="60" facs="tcp:30768:39"/>
                           <p n="7">7ly. That ſtrong purgations, offering vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the vital principles, exaſperates and makes them more irregular and defective, and thereby promotès rather than abates the ſtrength of this diſeaſe: But purgation or abſterſion rightly inſtituted (not every purge that makes you go to ſtool) is convenient and helpful in the Cure.</p>
                           <p n="8">8ly. That Scurvy-graſs, Watercreſſes, Brook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, moſt frequently uſed for the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> in Diet-drinks, Syrup, and juice, is not the ſpecifick remedy againſt the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> that is, challenging a peculiar propriety and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vertue againſt this diſeaſe before other Medicines; but comes far ſhort of other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines (though good, and may be more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly uſed) in their activity and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of the digeſtions to their primitive vigour and rectitude of their office and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                           <p n="9">9ly. That <hi>Cochlearia</hi> &amp;c. does not reſiſt this diſeaſe by a ſpecifick, peculiar antipathy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the occult malignity and products thereof; but by reſtoring and roborating the digeſtive faculties, by their ſaline vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing vertues, <hi>natura reliquum perficiente;</hi> which endowments are not ſpecifick, but common.</p>
                           <p n="10">10ly. That the diſeaſes complicated with the <hi>Scurvy</hi> are not cured by their own pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30768:39"/>Medicines, uſually effectual; unleſs they have reſpect to this diſeaſe, and that which is antiſcorbutical added to their ſpecifick vertues; or alternatively uſed: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſcorbutick Conſumptions, Fevers, Dropſies, Gouts, Aſtmaes, &amp;c. will not be ſubdued and yield obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of Cure.</p>
                           <p>I have now proſecuted this diſeaſe, and made diſquiſition into the nature of it, ſo far as time will give me leave at preſent: ſomething more I have to ſay upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but want due leaſure to deliver it to you, and therefore muſt defer, and wait for an opportunity to reviſe and augment this Treatiſe. What follows are the Medicines I uſe in the cure of this diſeaſe.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb facs="tcp:30768:40"/>
                           <p>Arcana Artis</p>
                           <p>Spagyricè fideliter &amp; Cura ſingulari, propria inſpectione praeparata.</p>
                           <p>Poteſtatum vitalium deficientium Virtute reſuſcitativa &amp; inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante dotata.</p>
                           <p>In levamen aegrorum ad praxim ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodata; &amp; ad morbos contumaces domandum valentiſſima.</p>
                           <p>Uſu &amp; experientia quam ſae piſſime probata.</p>
                           <p>Modo exhibendi, doſi, vehiculo, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, cum diſcrimine ſexuum aetatum, virium, pro re nata &amp; eorum natura, legibus appoſitè reſtricta.</p>
                           <p>Quicquid aliud de his curioſus, vel difficili morborum complexu coreptus cautè dubitabit; me conſulat, ſupplebo.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Everardus Maynwaringe,</hi> M. D.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
               <text xml:lang="eng">
                  <front>
                     <div type="title_page">
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:40"/>
                        <p>Antiſcorbutick MEDECINES, Exactly prepared and fitted for the principal caſes that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in Practice.</p>
                        <p>Largely endowed in univerſality, oppoſing many and grand DISEASES, Limitted and diſtinguiſhed in their Appropriation and Virtues.</p>
                        <p>Regulated praeciſely in their Uſe, by fit Doſes, proper Vehicles, due times, with reſpect to ſtrength, Sex and Age.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> under S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1664.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="preface">
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:41"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:41"/>
                        <head>PREFACE.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former diſcourſe having traced the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> from its infancy and generation to its full ſtrength and growth, its chief places of reſidence, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of appearance and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous deformity: it remains now to propoſe ſome effectual means to check and ſubdue the prevailing power of this ſpreading diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, that dayly grows and increaſerh to the ruin and decay of Nature; being poſſeſſed and ſeated in the vital principles, ſeducing and conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to enormity and defection from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity in which they were planted by Nature.</p>
                        <p>And having ſtrictly ſurveyed the condition and nature of this diſeaſe, with its variety of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and additional ſtrength, being ready to join with any morbifick cauſe, and be transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: I was unwilling to ſit down here &amp; reſt with a contemplative knowledge of the diſeaſe,, and
<pb facs="tcp:30768:42"/>leave the greateſt part of the work undone; the ſubduing and vanquiſhing of it by powerfull Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: nor being willing to commit the remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning grand part to the induſtry and care of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for good Reaſons;) I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laboured to form medicinal Inſtruments and prevalent means to oppoſe this Gigantick Monſter; being alwaies ready prepared for my own Patients, and thoſe that deſire the benefit of them: Namely, the <hi>Scorbute Pills</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Elixir,</hi> efficatious Medicines for the purpoſes appointed; with ſufficient Inſtructions here annexed, for their proper and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious uſe.</p>
                        <p>I ſhall not recount the benefits and advantage that many have received by them, nor publiſh the Perſons, (a way practiſed by ſome Quacks to induce credit to their Medicines, though the ſtories be oftentimes feigned, or effects fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and unduly imputed) but leave every one to beleeve of them what they pleaſe, if my word be not ſufficient to paſs for their reputation.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>LONDON, Next the blew Boar on Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Hill.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>E. M.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </front>
                  <body>
                     <div type="medicines">
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:30768:42"/>
                           <head>Scorbute Pills.</head>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Scorbute Pills</hi> are efficacious againſt the defects and errors of digeſtion in the firſt, ſecond, and third Office: In the firſt Office, namely, in all diſeaſes of the ſtomack, requiring pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and cleanſing downwards, this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is very proper; it evacuates and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loads a heavy oppreſſed ſtomack, clogged with indigeſted or depraved matter, that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts good food retained, or duls the Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and hinders digeſtion; prevents Fluxes, Gripings and pains in the ſtomack and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Cholick and Iliack paſſions, by taking away their cauſes, and leaving a grateful aſtriction and roboration upon the parts.</p>
                           <p>By their abſterſive quality, they remove crude viſcous phlegm impacted in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rugated Tunicles of the ſtomack and guts, being a receptacle for inflation and wind. They deſtroy Worms, and prevent their bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by carrying away the putrid matter whereof they are generated; they correct a nauſeating and belching ſtomack; make the ſtomack clean and fit for the reception of wholſom food, and not till then can you expect good nutriment.</p>
                           <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30768:43"/>
                           <p>In the ſubſequent digeſtions, and ſplenetick diſeaſes, they are powerfully abſterſive and a peritive, opening obſtructions of the Spleen, Gall, Meſentery, Liver and Reins, removing their morbifick cauſes, which produce a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chectick, or ill habit of body, the Scurvy, Dropſies, hypocondriack Melancholy, Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>Theſe Pills cleanſe and evacuate gently, whereby the fore-named parts are exonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſcharged of crude, coagulated, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved fermenting matter, which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there congeſted, or tranſmitted, various ſymptoms do ariſe in ſeveral parts of the body, appearing in a ſcorbutick difformity: as laſſitude, debility, and decay of ſeveral functions in the body, from fruſtrated and corrupt digeſtions: Fluxes from Crudities, or ſtimulation of acrimonious qualities, with eroſions and torſions of the guts: febrifick aeſtuations, turgid ebullitions, and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fermentation, producing various diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes and erratick pains; flatulent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentions, painfull compreſſions, anguſt and difficult breathing; obſtructions of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and ductures, from ſlimy and viſcous coagulations; cauſing unnatural retention of excrements which ought duly to be voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; impeding and retarding the expedite and free conveyance of nutriment, made degenerate &amp; depraved by a ſluggiſh paſſage
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30768:43"/>and impure commixture in the way; from whence Atrophies and ſcorbutick Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſpots, and defaedations of the skin; the ſpirits alſo obtunded in motion, inactive and torpid, dark and impure, being but the rarefactions and ſubtiliated extractions from depraved matter, alien and counterfeit; from whence dulneſs, heavineſs, and unwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſadneſs.</p>
                           <p>Theſe ſymptoms, and many more in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſons, are variouſly complicated, more or fewer, this with that, according to the plurality and complication of cauſes, which makes ſcorbutick perſons to be differently and variouſly affected.</p>
                           <p>For the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> theſe Pills are the beſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſive and purgative Medecine I ever made uſe of, in any the fore-named caſes, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no bad impreſſion behind, or debility upon the parts, as moſt purgatives do, and are offenſive to Nature and diſguſtful, though <hi>per accidens</hi> auxiliary and helpful, by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome material morbifick cauſe, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire correction and roboration of parts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
                           <p>For Hydropick Infirmities and watery tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of the body, whether univerſal, puffing up the whole body, as the <hi>Anaſarca:</hi> or in particular parts, as the <hi>Hydrocephalus,</hi> being a collection of water in the head: or the <hi>Hydrops pectoris,</hi> in the cavity of the breſt:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30768:44"/>or <hi>Aſcites</hi> in the belly: or <hi>Hydrocele,</hi> when the Cod is filled with water like a bladder: and ſometines in the legs only.</p>
                           <p>In any of theſe caſes, theſe Pills are very profitable, and do evacuate ſerous, or watry humors, accumulated and preternaturally retained in the body.</p>
                           <p>They are Aperitive, reſolutive, and diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, diſſolving coagulated matter that obſtruct the urinary ductures, provokes the Reins to diſcharge their office, in freeing the body from ſuperfluous watry humors, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting and tranſmitting them by urine, which is the due regiment and imperial po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the kidneys.</p>
                           <p>They open obſtructions in Women whoſe Courſes are ſtopt contrary to the cuſtom of Nature, and brings them into their right order; they clenſe the matrix, and evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate noxious humours collected there, diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate vapours, and is profitably uſed by thoſe who are ſubject to fits of the Mother.</p>
                           <p>For diſeaſes of the head they are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, but fit and efficacious againſt infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, afflicting the Brain and Nerves; by eradicating their occaſional cauſes that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire abſterſion and evacuation in the lower regions of the body.</p>
                           <p>Diſeaſes attributed to the head, for the moſt part do ariſe from inferior parts, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by their impurities, obſtructions and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30768:44"/>diſtempers; for one that is <hi>idiopathically</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, ten is <hi>Sympathically</hi> affected, by conſent of parts, and tranſmiſſion of ſome <hi>morbifick</hi> matter thither; but the foundation of the diſeaſe is elſewhere, and to that part muſt the Cure be directed.</p>
                           <p>And therefore if well obſerved, we fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently meet with, <hi>ſcorbutick palſies, ſcorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick convulſions, apoplexies, ſoporiferous,</hi> or ſleepy diſeaſes, falling ſickneſs, pains of the head, giddineſs, tremblings, deafneſs, dull fight and blindneſs: And all theſe arifing from the <hi>Scurvy</hi> or <hi>Scorbutick</hi> impurity of the body oftentimes: And theſe are not cured but by <hi>antiſcorbutical medicines;</hi> and thoſe that endeavour otherwiſe with their <hi>ſpecifick</hi> and appropriate medicines to the parts where ſuch <hi>ſymptoms</hi> and diſeaſes do appear, labour in vain and are fruſtrate in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cures.</p>
                           <p>For thoſe that are troubled with Rheums ariſing from indigeſtion and crudities, theſe Pils are profitable; not ſo much that they attract rheum, but becauſe they cleanſe and ſtrengthen the digeſtions, and ſo the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent cauſe is cut off.</p>
                           <p>And for the ſame reaſon they are good in pectoral infirmities, diſeaſes of the breaſt, ariſing from phlegm and crude indigeſted humors, ſometimes ſharp or falt, cauſing pertinacious coughing, and diſturbing the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30768:45"/>Lungs in the performance of their office, by an unquiet irritation: ſometimes viſcous, tough and thick, ſtopping the pipes of the Lungs and veſſels for reſpiration; obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and occluding the pores of the Lungs, which ought to be pervious into the Cavity of the breaſt, whereby the air is drawn in with difficulty, although ſo thin a body and penetrating: from hence Aſthmaes, wheez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſhort and painful breathing; and in theſe caſes of obſtructions, the Lungs (or rather the intercoſtal muſcles) to ſupply this defect is forced to a double or ſwifter motion, that the heart ſhould not want air, neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in the performance of its noble office.</p>
                           <p>And that theſe infirmities are cauſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes from the Scurvy, none that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand will deny; and ſo great have theſe Scorbutick Aſthmaes been, that many have been ſuffocated in the extremity of a ſudden paroxiſm, or fit of this diſeaſe.</p>
                           <p>And not only difficulty of breathing, but anguſtneſs, compreſſion, palpitations of the heart, or heart-beating, and ſwoonings ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are cauſed by this diſeaſe: in ſuch caſes theſe Pils are proper and beneficial; they open obſtructions, diſſipate putrid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign vapours that afflict the heart, and diſturb the regularity of its motion.</p>
                           <p>There is alſo Scorbutick Conſumpſions,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30768:45"/>accompanied for the moſt part with a Hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick fever, whereby the body waſts and pines away, being defrauded of good nutriment, that ſhould ſupport and maintain the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but is converted into impure depraved matter and excrementitious; hereby the body is enfeebled and weak, the ſpirits hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, dull and ſad, the skin lax or looſe, the fleſh ſoft and waſting, and all the faculties languiſhing and declining.</p>
                           <p>In this caſe theſe Pills are a fit medecine to begin the Cure; then uſe the Elixir fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: but cooling drinks and reſtaurative Broths hurtful: <hi>Corpora impura quo plus nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triveris eo magis laeſeris:</hi> foul bodies the more you feed and endeavour to nouriſh them the worſe you make them.</p>
                           <p>Finally, for all occaſions where purgation and clenſing is neceſſary theſe Pills are fitly uſed, and is a univerſal medicine in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nor do they only clenſe and carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way excrementitious degenerate matter which occaſions many diſeaſes, (according to the diverſity of parts to which it is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and from conſent of parts though not tranſmitted) but alſo do roborate and ſtrengthen the parts in their paſſage, being amicable and friendly to Nature.</p>
                           <p>The Doſe for man or woman is 3 or 4 Pils; perhaps 5 Pils may be required; according to the ſtrength and condition of the body to operate.</p>
                           <pb n="72" facs="tcp:30768:46"/>
                           <p>So great a difference there is in bodies for purging, that two or three of theſe Pils are ſufficient for ſome, when as others will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire 4, or perhaps 5, if a robuſtick body: therefore try your body firſt with a leſſer Doſe; then if it require more, you may add to the next, and be not too Bold at firſt.</p>
                           <p>The times for taking them generally is thus, except good reaſon to the contrary: Take one Pill over night going to bed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaten but a light ſupper at 6 of the clock before; the next morning early in bed take the remaining part of the Doſe, and you may ſleep an hour after if you will; but lie not long in the morning: when you are up drink a little warm poſſet-drink, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear eating until dinner time; but drink you may.</p>
                           <p>Theſe Pils take thus every fourth or fifth day; and you will find it beſt to give ſuch intermiſſion: Chronick or old diſeaſes muſt have time to be eradicated, and you muſt reduce Nature from an ill habit by degrees, better than haſtily; as diſeaſes come on, gradually prevailing upon Nature; ſo Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by degrees muſt be reſtored again to its power and regularity: <hi>Cum natura malè ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinet repentinas mutationes.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But on the intermittng daies you are not forbidden every thing medicinal, but may take the following <hi>Elixir</hi> conveniently.</p>
                           <pb n="73" facs="tcp:30768:46"/>
                           <p>Concerning Doſes I muſt ſay ſomething more, that none may miſtake, but know what is meant by a Doſe.</p>
                           <p>A Doſe is the true quantity of a Medecine to be taken at once, or for one operation: A Doſe is not a ſet quantity (as ſome may ſuppoſe) to be given equally alike to all; but ſuch a proportion as is convenient for the condition of every body, to ſome more, to others leſs, according to ſtrength and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condition of the body in operation.</p>
                           <p>For the Doſes or quantities of Phyſick ſutable to every body (chiefly in purging) there is as much variety, as in the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of meat for every mans ſtomack: ſo much as will fully ſatisfie and be convenient for one man, may be too little for another, and too much perhaps for a third. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a regular diet, to the weaker ſort of perſons we allow a ſpare and ſlender diet; but to the ſtrong and luſty, firm and ſolid bodies, we allow a larger proportion, and that neceſſarily.</p>
                           <p>The ſame Rule in Phyſick is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to fit every one with a due quantity and Doſe, to ſtrong bodies more, to weaker leſs.</p>
                           <p>The Doſe of theſe Pills is not praeciſely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to a Pill, neither more nor leſs to all; but with ſome latitude, 3, 4, or 5 (being gentle in operation:) for the difference
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30768:47"/>of bodies is ſuch in operation, (eſpecially purging) that they require a different quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity oftentimes for their proportion, which cannot ſo exactly be determined and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the praeſcience of the moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſitian, but by rational conjecture, until the firſt experiment and trial of their bodies; and after the firſt Doſe, your own Reaſon and ability of body will prompt you in the next, whether to keep to the ſame, to augment or abate; Taking this caution, that 4 or 5 ſtools in a day is enough; and that number I intend you to aim at, and no more.</p>
                           <p>For example; if you have a ſtubborn bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, difficult and hard to purge, and your Phyſick works very little, the next Doſe you may take one Pill more: but if you have a lax gentle body and eaſie to purge, then take a leſſer Doſe, and abate a Pill, if the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer work too nimbly with you: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this as a neceſſary Caution, That you covet not ſtrong purges, to have many ſtools in a day (a common error) which offers violence to Nature, and forcibly ſweeping down both good and bad together; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chooſe to draw away the offending cauſe gently by degrees, giving Nature time for ſeparation, the pure from the impure and noxious: 4 or 5 ſtools in a day is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and you will find it much more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30768:47"/>Nature more kindly aſſiſting, and leſs weakned.</p>
                           <p>Some there are (brain-ſick fools) who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their Phyſick work a douzen times, think they have kept houſe for nothing, and their money caſt away, accounting the goodneſs of their Phyſick by the number of ſtools; but they deceive themſelves very much in deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtrong purgations, which weaken and impare Nature, leaving ſuch impreſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, ſometimes worſe than the diſeaſe they took them for.</p>
                           <p>Theſe Pills, although purgative, yet their chief vertue is not contained in the purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, but in other appropriate qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, oppoſing the ſeveral diſeaſes, to which the laxative adjunct property is but a Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid and ſubſidiary: nor muſt you expect alwaies the diſeaſe to be brought into the Cloſe-ſtool, there are other Conveyances and ways of emiſſion of Natures providing beſides the common back door.</p>
                           <p>Concerning preparation before purging, muck talked of, take this advice: That ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble bodies eaſily yielding obedince to gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purging Medecines, need no other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration than what Nature hath provided in the diſpoſition of their own bodies: for thoſe bodies that are hot and coſtive, it will be advantagious and facilitate their purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to eat ſtewed Prunes, or drink Whey
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30768:48"/>two or three daies before, which will prepare and open your body, make it more ſoluble and eaſie in purging.</p>
                           <p>For the manner of taking; whereas theſe Pills are appointed to be taken, one Pill o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver night, the other part in the morning; yet if you find any inconvenience thereby, you may take the whole Doſe in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very early; but if you have not a juſt cauſe of alteration, obſerve the former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
                           <p>For going abroad after your Pills, if you deſire it, or your occaſions require, take this advice: if your body be indifferent ſtrong, not apt upon ſmall occaſions to take cold, the weather temperate, having ordered the Doſe of your Pils to work but three or four times; you may then go abroad without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice; but if otherwiſe, it is better to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The Catholick</hi> Elixir.</head>
                           <p>BEfore I proceed to tell you the vertues and profitable uſe of this Medecine, I muſt firſt give you the reaſon of the Title, that none may ſtumble at it.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Catholick</hi> is univerſal; and this Medicine may be ſtiled ſo: not that it cures every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe', but that it is effectual againſt ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30768:48"/>or infirmity in every faculty, as they are thus divided and diſtinguiſhed into the natural, vital, animal, and genital faculties: and being thus endowed with a competent meaſure of univerſality, it may not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called a Catholick or univerſal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, ſince its vertue is extended to all the grand faculties.</p>
                           <p>But you may ask, why an univerſal Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine ſhould be compoſed and appointed for a particular diſeaſe, it being intended chiefly for the <hi>Scurvy?</hi> In anſwer to this; if you look into the preceding Tract, you will find the <hi>Scurvy</hi> not to be a ſingle diſeaſe, but a complication of diſeaſes, whoſe root, or branches, if arrived at ſome height, extend to all the faculties, bringing detriment and decay throughout the body.</p>
                           <p>For the word <hi>Elixir,</hi> concerning its Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie and derivation, there are ſeveral opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; ſome will have it from the Arabick, others from the Greek; but I ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with that: it is ſufficient that you underſtand it is a Medicine of noble deſcent, and may have the uſe of it: If you expect I ſhould tell you of what it is made, and the proceſs how? you muſt pardon me there, it does not belong to you.</p>
                           <p>If an Artiſt ſhould view the ingredients of this Medicine, before operation upon them, would determin them only for the deficiency
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30768:49"/>of the natural faculties, and their parts; as the Stomack, Spleen; Gall, Meſentery, Liver, Reins, &amp;c. but being ſpiritalized, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duated and advanced; they do extend fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as alſo, for that the other faculties do depend very much upon the integrity of theſe, as well as the compleatneſs of their own peculiar organs, by and in which they execute their ſeveral functions: for, either by tranſmiſſion or conſent the reſt ſuffer if theſe be injured.</p>
                           <p>I ſhall not demonſtrate this truth, and explain it further; being a Doctrine not ſo neceſſary for you to know: but proceed to give you an account of the vertues this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is pregnant with, and manner of uſe.</p>
                           <p>And firſt of their eſſicacy in the natural functions.</p>
                           <p>This <hi>Elixir</hi> is uſed with good ſucceſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt moſt infirmities ſeated in the Stomack, Spleen, Guts, Pancreas, Meſentery, Liver, and Reins, eſpecially if they be languid and weak; degenerating and falling off from their duties; being obſtructed, loaded, or clogged with crude, depraved and indigeſted matter; wanting ſpirit and vigor, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteneſs of ferment fit for their proper works: This Medicine does acuate and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorate, giving ſpirit and activity in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their duties.</p>
                           <p>For ſurfeits, oppreſſion, and overcharging
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30768:49"/>the Stomack, it is a ſure Remedy; working off the offending matter, cheriſhing and refreſhing the ſtomack. It excites and quickens a dull or weak appetite, and procures a good digeſtion, (which is the main pillar of health) being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry auxiliary and aſſiſtant to the ſtomacks di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtive ferment deficient and decayed, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunded and overlaid with crudities or depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved matter from intemperance, incongruous diet, and bad cuſtoms.</p>
                           <p>By its Balſamick Amaritude, is healing and grateful to a wateriſh, crude, raw ſtomack: corrects nauſeouſneſs and vomiting (ſafely in breeding women) ſuppreſſing and ſubduing the offenſive cauſes, leaving a good aſtriction upon the ſtomack, and roborating the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty.</p>
                           <p>Is helpful to thoſe moleſted with belching, and grip'd with wind in the ſtomack, or guts, by correcting and digeſting crudities, and preventing a diſcordant fermentation the cauſes thereof.</p>
                           <p>Amends a ſtrong offenſive breath, and checks unſavory riſings in the ſtomack from fruſtrated and corrupt digeſtions: prevents and deſtroys worms bred from ſuch putrid indigeſted mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                           <p>This <hi>Elixir</hi> hath an aperitive and opening power, and is profitably uſed by thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted with hypocondriack Melancholy; that have obſtructed Livers or Spleens; diſtended
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30768:50"/>and full in the ſides under the ſhort ribs; or pained there, by reaſon of wind and humors obſtructed in motion.</p>
                           <p>'Tis a good Medicine in the cure of Dropſies, and beneficial for Hydropick perſons, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining thereto and troubled with a watry hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in any part: it digeſts ſuperfluous humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, opens obſtructions of the veſſels leading to the reins; excites the attractive faculty of the Kidneys which before were ſluggiſh, imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, or impedited in the attraction and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of urine; roborates the parts and confirms them in their duties.</p>
                           <p>For intermitting Fevers, called Agues, <hi>quotidian, tertian,</hi> or <hi>quartan,</hi> it is very good; they being ſeated in the fore-named parts, to which this Medicine is properly aſſiſtant and auxiliary; diſchargeth its vertue upon the parts ſo affected, alters and ſubdues their morbifick cauſes, and haſtens their diſeaſes to a period, by removing their fuel of conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and continuance; and afterwards does ſtrengthen thoſe parts, debilitated and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſuch diſeaſes harbouring there; and raſeth out the bad impreſſions left behind them, which breed future inconveniencies, and are foundations laid for other diſeaſes; which will ſucceed, if not prevented after this manner by good Medecine, to clenſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the parts; as frequently we do obſerve in practice.</p>
                           <pb n="81" facs="tcp:30768:50"/>
                           <p>In the vital faculties this Elixir is of good uſe, and beneficial for thoſe that are troubled with palpitations of the heart, anguſtneſs and compreſſion there; ariſing moſt frequently from vitiated digeſtions and ſcorbutick fecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, an ill affected ſpleen, or matrix; from whence noxious vapours ariſe, and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the vital Spirits, which afflict and irritate the heart to this diſtempered mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and if the cauſe be very great and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, ſometimes ſwooning is cauſed thereby, as in Fits of the Mother, and paſſions of the ſpleen: this medicine diſſipates the vapours, and prevents their cauſes of generation, by rectifying and roborating the parts from whence they proceed.</p>
                           <p>It is good in aſthmaes and ſtoppings of the breaſt from crude Phlegme; opens the pipes of the Lungs and helps difficulty of breathing; ſtrengthens the Lungs and is very advantagious for Conſumptive Perſons, and that have a faint ſhort breath, or that are moleſted with a troubleſom and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Cough, inclining and diſpoſing them to a Conſumption.</p>
                           <p>'Tis Cordial and reſtaurative, cheriſheth and refreſheth the Spirits, by the aromatick vertue and pleaſant tranſpiration of its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, raiſing the Spirits and affecting them with delight.</p>
                           <p>In the animal faculties, and for infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30768:51"/>of the head; as Convulſion, falling Sickneſs, Vertigo or giddineſs, ſleepineſs laſſitude and dulneſs, pains of the head, rheumes and ſuperfluous moiſture, this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is very good, and beneficial to ſtrengthen the brain and nerves; to ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, leſſen and abate the antecedent cauſes of theſe infirmities, generated in other parts, although they appear and ſhew themſelves moſt here.</p>
                           <p>And although this medicine is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly appropriate to ſupply the natural faculties than the other, <hi>primo intentionaliter;</hi> yet <hi>conſequenter</hi> and in effect, the vital, the animal and generative faculties is improved and made more vigorous in their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and functions; and alſo freed from many diſeaſes by the rectitude and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the natural faculties, both in reſpect of prevention and cure: for that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral faculties are the <hi>baſis</hi> and foundation of the reſt in conſervation; and are ſupported from thence as the Tree from <hi>radix,</hi> the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from the root: and defects, impediments and decay of the natural faculties, cauſeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, diſorder and infirmities in the reſt, by tranſmiſſion or conſent.</p>
                           <p>And though the Symptoms appear in one part, and diſorder one faculty more apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the cauſe often lies obſcure and is the proper defect of another; between which you
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30768:51"/>would think there were no relation, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce or incommodation one from the other.</p>
                           <p>If the natural faculties be vitiated in their functions; all the reſt decline from rectitude, and abate in their vigour: as in the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> firſt the natural faculties are debilitated and diſordered; then from hence the vital, the animal and genital do degenerate, and are diſcompoſed; and there is ſufficient reaſon, for that theſe are ſupplied from thence: and when the natural faculties are reſtored to their vigour and rectitude; the other alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of this change and are reſtored in a great meaſure; except the particular Organs of thoſe faculties be made incapable.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore and for theſe Cauſes, if I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the vertues of this Medicine yet farther, and ſhew its power and prevalency againſt more infirmities, I do not aſcribe above what it doth juſtly challenge.</p>
                           <p>In the genital parts: if I ſhould tell you it were good againſt deficiency in generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and defects of the ſeed: as crudeneſs, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs degenerate pravity, and infaecundity, the cauſes of barrenneſs, perhaps you would think I go beyond my bounds; but I could eaſily prove, and make it a rational aſſertion, deductive from the principles of Phyſick, beſides what is ſaid before; but my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here is not ſo much to improve your knowledge as your health; the preſervation
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30768:52"/>of the bodily functions in their integrity; and reſtoration of them declining, languiſhing and deviating from their primitive rectitude; if your faith will not put you upon the tryal, I ſhall not raiſe arguments to convince your reaſon and perſwade, believe what you pleaſe.</p>
                           <p>It is very good for Women that have loſt their Complexion, looking pale, yellow and ill coloured; by reaſon of that weakneſs cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Whites, or wanting the due courſe of nature, by reaſon of obſtructions from cold, bad dyet, ill cuſtoms and vitiated digeſtions; or a diſtempered melancholy mind; which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs nature in her conſtant order, and due regiment of preſervation: it is very profitably uſed during the time of their monthly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; it procures them effectually.</p>
                           <p>For thoſe that have ſores, or abound with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humours which enforceth them to keep iſſues open, to prevent greater inconvenience &amp; danger; this Medicine applyes to the ſprings from whence they iſſue, and where they are bred; prevents them in their cauſes, in ſome perſons; in all it abates and leſſens in the quantity; corrects and alters the ſtinking cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt quality, and makes your body more ſweet and wholſome.</p>
                           <p>This Elixir as it is properly uſed in the particular caſes mentioned ſingly, ſo likewiſe in the ſame conjunct and variouſly compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and graduated, amounting to, or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:30768:52"/>the denomination and title of the Scurvy; againſt which this medicine is very effectuall, and neceſſarily follows the uſe of the preceding pills, to ſtrengthen the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties after abſtertion and cleanſing; whereby the like Scorbutick impurity and ill ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms ariſing from thence, for the future is prevented, and a return of the diſeaſe prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited (in a regular due courſe of living) for, as the diſeaſe did grow by errors and defects in the digeſtions, producing ſuch various ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes; ſo are they prevented by aſſiſting the digeſtions, and preſerving them in their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity &amp; due courſe of nature from declenſion.</p>
                           <p>For which purpoſe and intention this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is prevalent, to roborate the faculties and principal parts ordained for thoſe offices: reſolveth and volatiſeth coagulate and fixed matter; attenuates and rarefies groſs ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding humours which cauſe obſtructions, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and pains: reſiſts putrifaction, depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates and renovates the blood from a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate condition, ſtained with Scorbutick fecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and impurity, reſtoring its balſamick na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and genuine proprieties.</p>
                           <p>Of neceſſary uſe for aged and weak perſons whoſe faculties fall off from their integrity, and abated in their vigour, do perform but weakly and deficiently; as alſo for ſuch who are recovering or lately recovered from ſome great diſeaſe, which hath enervated and debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litated
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30768:53"/>all the functions, leaving the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter and impreſſions of an evil cauſe behind upon the parts, chiefly where they were ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which renders them indiſpoſed and unfit in their duties, and layes the foundation of new diſeaſes to enſue from hence.</p>
                           <p>In ſuch caſes this medicine is a good aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant and requiſite auxiliary help to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, and reſtoration of vigour in a competent meaſure, if there be a capacity of reſtoration in the parts remaining, where ſuch faculties do reſide and are exerciſed.</p>
                           <p>And that you may uſe this medicine to the beſt advantage, take this advice; that if your body be foul, firſt cleanſe with a doſe or two of the Scorbute pills; then begin with this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixir to ſtrengthen the faculties, and you will daily perceive a growing benefit incouraging you to continue the uſe thereof; which is done with the leaſt of trouble not incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating your occaſions; that amidſt affairs, in journeys, it prevents you not in your law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cuſtoms, or tyes you to inconvenient ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance, nor of the ſeaſon, but is profitably uſed at any time of the year.</p>
                           <p>Take this caution: be not too haſty in your expectations, and leave not the uſe of it too ſoon; your diſeaſe came on gradually, and was longer in breeding than you imagine, though the ſymptoms or ſignes of it appear to you ſuddainly and lately; perhaps ſome years, or many years have laid the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30768:53"/>and but now makes a diſcovery, being arrived at ſome heigth: you muſt then in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon allow ſome time for eradication and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall; ſince nature will not admit of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and ſuddain changes, but is diſturbed and injured at ſuch rude dealing: therefore take time as nature, and the medicine does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; nor will you want incouragement to perſevere, but have daily advantage againſt your infirmity.</p>
                           <p>The full doſe for Man or Woman of ſtrength, is thirty drops: for twelve years old, twenty drops: for five years old, ten drops.</p>
                           <p>And obſerve this rule; that at the firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, you begin but with half the doſe that is appointed for your age: as thus; thirty drops is appointed for a Man; let him begin with fifteen drops, and then augment two or three drops every day after, until he aſcend to thirty, and there continue.</p>
                           <p>Take it (in bed if you be very weak) in a ſpoonful of good Canary; and one ſpoonful after to waſh your mouth; every morning, faſting an hour and a half after: and likewiſe at five of the clock in the afternoon: (thoſe dayes only excepted that you take pills) but you are not ſo ſtrictly to obſerve the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon; that if your occaſions do not well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; as when you muſt be abroad, or the like; you may omit.</p>
                           <p>Note that this Elixir is never to be taken or taſted alone, but mixed in ſome liquor.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="88" facs="tcp:30768:54"/>
                           <head>Of Diſeaſes and Medicines.</head>
                           <p>IN the preceding tract of the Scurvy, you may remember that in the body there are ſeveral digeſtions and digeſtive offices for the preparation of food, ſubordinate one to the other, whereby aliment is prepared gradually untill it receive the complement and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of aſſimilation for nutrition, and conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body.</p>
                           <p>Theſe digeſtive offices as they are the grand laboratories of the body neceſſary for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ſo occaſionally by their errors and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from their integrity of operation, moſt diſeaſes in the body do ariſe, and are planted radically in ſome principal member the manſion aſſigned where theſe faculties do reſide and exerciſe their power &amp; juriſdiction.</p>
                           <p>And although Diſeaſes are very numerous and various in their denominations, ſometimes from the diverſity of ſymptoms that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them, as if they were the off-ſpring of divers Parents, by their ſeveral faces and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: yet trace them up to their original deſcent, you may find many to ſpring from one radix, and own the ſame occaſional cauſes, notwithſtanding their diſſimilarity, in their growth and progreſs; yet their affinity is ſuch by birth, that with a ſingle medicine, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:30768:54"/>two may be required, rightly prepared and fitted for the work, you ſhall eradicate or deſtroy the root; and the branches that grow from thence though ſpread in divers parts of the body, ſhall whither and fall away.</p>
                           <p>It is not neceſſary therefore to multiply me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for every particular ſpmptom that ſprings from a diſeaſe, but to level and aim at the root or fountain from whence they ſpring.</p>
                           <p>The diſcourſe is metaphorical, and carries illuſtration with it; but to make it more plain and facile to your apprehenſion, and to ſhew you the verity of it, take this example for a Confirmation.</p>
                           <p>A Phyſitian coming to his Patient finds him thus affected; feavouriſh, head ach, pained at the Stomach, grip'd in the belly, a looſeneſs: all which may proceed from one cauſe, and will be cured with one good medicine.</p>
                           <p>The cauſe producing all theſe ſymptomes, may be <hi>acor indebitus;</hi> a domeſtick luxuriant, or peregrine acidity in the firſt digeſtion: hence a febrile temper ariſeth, from the Spirits tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuating, agitated and troubled at this exorbitant hoſtile quality; the ſtomach pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the lancing of its ſharpneſs; the head ach by conſent from thence; the belly grip'd and collick pains by tranſmiſſion of this pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant acidity with the chyle; a flux or looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs procured by the ſame purging quality, ſtimulating and provoking the expulſive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30768:55"/>which endeavours to eject and expel it,</p>
                           <p>You ſee that one morbifick cauſe may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce various ſymptoms and effects: and it is unneceſſary, yea improper and without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to apply particular medicines to each, not reſpecting the cauſe; and herein a wiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian is known from him that is otherwiſe.</p>
                           <p>In the caſe recited, ſome there are, and thoſe thinking they do <hi>ſecundum artem,</hi> will preſcribe a <hi>Julip</hi> to abate or prevent the feaver in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing: apply a frontale to the head, or give a ſpecifick medicine for the head ach: an emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for pain of the ſtomach and griping of the guts, which allayes for the preſent, but ſoon after it is received into the body, turns ſour and joynes with the morbifick cauſe.</p>
                           <p>For the looſneſs, perhaps you will give an aſtringent medicine and lock the Thief up: but I will imagine you to be wiſer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult about a Clyſter, to draw away the cauſe, the peccant humour that ſtimulates, and when that is come away, nature being no longer provoked with an inteſtine enemy, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in peace to her former ſedate temper.</p>
                           <p>This is ſomething you ſay, and plauſible; but what Clyſter will you give (in this caſe) to attract the peccant humour, which is the Chyle in the ſtomack, alienated with a luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant acidity? your Phlegmagoga and Chola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goga, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know, but Chylogoga, I know none, nor you: but you will ſay, the guts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30768:55"/>emptied by any Clyſter, the ſtomack alſo will be exhauſted and drained, by the attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on below: if I ſhould grant your reaſon to be good, the practice notwithſtanding is not good: for, if this exorbitant quality in the Chyle mentioned, be the only diſturbance, as it is in the caſe, then the tranſmutation ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and ſubduing of the ſame, is ſufficient, and an exact Cure without evacuation and ſubducting the Chyle: but this, a ſingle Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizate medicine will perform, <hi>cito, tuto, jucunde,</hi> without any other help &amp; means, &amp; all ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms ariſing from the ſaid cauſe ſhall ceaſe.</p>
                           <p>In jurious it is to make exhauſtion of the body, when the blotting out of an aliene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or the taming of a luxuriant quality is the ſcope of the Cure; which may be done, <hi>ſalvo ſucco nutritio:</hi> and like to this is the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying of medicines impertinently, when a ſingle medicine will effect the intention, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the axiom; <hi>fruſtra fit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>An able practiſed Phyſitian, rightly princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled in the nature of Diſeaſes, and expert in pharmacy, may well contract his practice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of a few medicines; ſuch I mean as are graduated to a high pitch of energy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving acquired a latitude of univerſality, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate with the grand faculties, oppoſing all their deficiencies and depraved operations.</p>
                           <p>Indigeſtion and depraved digeſtion are the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30768:56"/>foundations of many diſeaſes and bad ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms: as vomiting, nauſeouſneſs, wind, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, pains, loſs of appetite, fulneſs, heat and thirſt, in the ſtomack primarily affected; by conſent, and tranſmiſſion of the ſame morbifick cauſe, divers parts are variouſly affected, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing fluxes, feavors, diſtention of the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chonders, Cholick, head-achs, obſtructions and pains in ſeveral parts: the radix and fountain from whence theſe ſpring is the ſtomack or firſt digeſtion; the ſymptoms &amp; products are branched and ſpread into ſeveral parts of the body: now for the cure, not many medicines are required, but one or two efficacious and proper, aiming at the cauſe, directed by the hand of art; a good abſterſive and roborating medicine after to confirm the faculty, is both prevention and cure.</p>
                           <p>I might farther exemplifie and make it plain, by the paralell caſes in the other facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but <hi>verbum ſat ſapienti,</hi> and others it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not, therefore I paſs on.</p>
                           <p>But I would not be miſtaken herein, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould think I countenance the Panphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macums of Quacks, by them decanted and cryed up for their excelling vertues, &amp; univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal property to oppoſe aery diſeaſe: I know it is a grand deluſion and cheat that is upon thoſe who believe ſuch aery empty boaſters; but that an elaborate perite Artiſt, ſolidly grounded in the true principles of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30768:56"/>may prepare medicines endowed with a large portion of univerſality, bringing within the lattiude and circle of their ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, very many diſeaſes, reſtoring the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties decayed, the great engins of our bodies; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borating the <hi>primum mobile inſtrumentaliter,</hi> and of this, reaſon and experiment can demonſtrate the truth, and convince the unbeliever.</p>
                           <p>The greateſt deficiency I have obſerved, in ſome, though otherwiſe ſufficiently ſtockt with Learning and accompliſhed, is in Medicines; I mean the Pharmacopoietical part; but if more time were improved in that practice, it would much compenſate their labour, and redound to their ſucceſs, honour and advantage: they were then Maſters of their ſecrets which now are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, the conſequents whereof <hi>ſero nimis ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt;</hi> and I muſt ſay that <hi>Doctor Medicinae</hi> ought to be <hi>peritum in medicinis,</hi> and that practically: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines then would be more nicely and exactly ſcruted into, their defects ſupplyed and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their ſuperfluous accumulation of ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in many compoſitions abated; many errors in preparation and compoſition corrected, not to be known, becauſe not experimented by their own inſpection, thinking <hi>a fiat ſeeundum artem ſufficient.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Hence it is ſome diſeaſes paſs for incurable, through the penury &amp; deficiency of medicines, not for the quantity, but quality, being meanly graduated, not extracted from their feculency
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30768:57"/>and terenity, but remain complexed in their heterogene parts, with a <hi>ſuper</hi> addition of ſugar, honey, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to drown the energy and power of the medicine.</p>
                           <p>For variety of medicines, there were never more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, frivolous, and I may ſay dangerous, from the multitude of ſpurious pretended Chymiſts, illigiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and not the Sons of Art; being ignorant of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical principles, and the abſtruſe natures of what they deal with, blindly run upon many errors, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding their caſual experiments upon the People, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the titles of laudable approved Medicines: others are guilty of great abuſes, wilfully for advantage, to ſpare coſt and labour, thus, moſt places abound with baſe Medicines which brings defamation to Phyſitians lingring ſickneſſes and death to their Patients.</p>
                           <p>The charge incumbent upon Phyſitians in theſe caſes, for prevention, is not ſmall; and it much concerns them to be very circumſpect what Medicines they make uſe of; and the quality of the Artiſt they truſt: and I muſt aſſirm that an expert knowledge in the Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoietical part of Phyſick, do as much belong to a Phyſitian and is ſo neceſſary, that without it he cannot be ſaid to be compleat; for, he that is not an Artiſt herein cannot direct and correct as he ought, by the promptings of a bare contemplative knowledge: and although he excludes himſelf from inſpection into the practick part, as an unneceſſary trouble and below the dignity of his title, yet he is not excuſed thereby, but his reputation payes for the miſcarriages and abuſes therein.</p>
                           <p>But this is an excurſion beyond the limits of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, at the entrance of the diſcourſe, and therefore I wave the proſecution.</p>
                        </div>
                        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:57"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:30768:58"/>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
            </group>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
